<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Observations upon the statute of 22 Car. II. cap. I. entituled, An act to prevent and suppress seditious conventicles by Sir Edmund Saunders, Kt. ...</title>
            <author>Saunders, Edmund, Sir, d. 1683.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 136 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 83 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62224</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S742</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9546</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12384414</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12384414</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60812</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62224)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60812)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 227:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Observations upon the statute of 22 Car. II. cap. I. entituled, An act to prevent and suppress seditious conventicles by Sir Edmund Saunders, Kt. ...</title>
                  <author>Saunders, Edmund, Sir, d. 1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[15], 23, 125 [i.e. 123] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Dring ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The Lord Saunders ... did write this explanation ... so far as page 79 ... for the residue, as it had not the same authour, so neither doth it expect the same authority, it being added as an essay to supply what was left undone"--To the reader.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 125 [i.e. 123].</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [14]-[15].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Act to prevent and supress seditious conventicles.</term>
               <term>Conventicle act, 1670.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60812:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60812:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>OBSERVATIONS UPON THE STATUTE OF 22 CAR. II. <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. Entituled, An ACT to Prevent and Suppreſs Seditious Conventicles.</p>
            <p>By Sir <hi>Edmund Saunders,</hi> Kt. late Lord Chief Juſtice of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Dring,</hi> at the Corner of <hi>Chancery-Lane</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:60812:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60812:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Reader.</head>
            <p>TO Recommend this ſmall Treatiſe to thy peruſal, there needs no more then the Title with the Authour's Name, whoſe Loyalty, Integrity, and profound Learning in all
<pb facs="tcp:60812:3"/>the Laws of this Realm, were ſo eminent and conſpicuous both while he was at the Bar, and after his deſerved ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement to the Bench, that 'twould be imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to tell thee what a Reverence was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways paid to his Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; His Memory is ſo freſh, that I cannot ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe thee ignorant of the ſame, or void of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found
<pb facs="tcp:60812:3"/>reſpect to his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry name, for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of which, this Manual is publiſhed, as alſo for the publick good of the Realm, which was his end in its Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition; the immediate oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of writing theſe Obſervations was to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify the Requeſts of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of his Majeſty's Juſtices of the Peace for the County of <hi>Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:60812:4"/>who deſired his Opinion in ſundry points upon this Statute for the better Government of themſelves in the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution hereof with ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty from the malitious Suits of the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Party, who were, and always are ready to take advantage of the leaſt ſlip or miſtake of any of the King's Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the Peace. The
<pb facs="tcp:60812:4"/>Lord <hi>Saunders</hi> being ſenſible thereof, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of the great uſe of this Law, and the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of its Proſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in order to preſerve the publick Peace and Quiet of the Kingdom, did write this Explana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it even while he was Lord Chief Juſtice of <hi>England,</hi> it being all of his own Hand-writing, ſo far
<pb facs="tcp:60812:5"/>as <hi>page 79.</hi> where you will ſee the Additio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals printed with this mark before them ': The great multiplicity of buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in his Place, and the unhappy indiſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Body did prevent the completion thereof, he often wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for but a few hours time to perfect it; For the reſidue, as it had not the ſame Authour,
<pb facs="tcp:60812:5"/>ſo neither doth it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the ſame Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, it being added as an Eſſay to ſupply what was left undone, and yet the ſupplement may be not without its uſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made as near as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to the Lord <hi>Saun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi>'s ſenſe in other Paragraphs, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his Method and Rule are the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions made even in
<pb facs="tcp:60812:6"/>ſuch manner as may moſt advance the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, and ſuppreſs the Miſchief intended by this Law, and are moſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grounded upon appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Opinions and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions of the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es on this Law, and other Laws of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. For the Subject, 'tis well known that this Act never received a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny publick. Animadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,
<pb facs="tcp:60812:6"/>and yet doth perhaps need an Expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation as much as thoſe againſt Recuſancy, on which there have been Obſervations made and Printed, and not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Approbation. For the ſeaſonableneſs of this Publication, there needs no other Apology than what the Age we live, and the Book it ſelf do beſpeak, and if it may
<pb facs="tcp:60812:7"/>prove any way ſervicea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Publick, by being helpfull to the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices and other Officers of the King's Peace, the Reverend Authour's Deſign, as well as that of the Publiſher will both be accompliſhed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:60812:7"/>
            <head>Some Books Printed for <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Dring</hi> over againſt the <hi>Inner-Temple</hi> Gate in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Law, in Folio.</head>
            <p>THE Statutes at large, from <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Charta,</hi> to this preſent year 1682. in Paragraphs and Sections, with References to the Books of the Law, and an exact Table: By <hi>Joſeph Keble</hi> of <hi>Grays</hi>-Inn <abbr>Eſq</abbr> in <hi>folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Kebles</hi> Aſſiſtance to Juſtices of the Peace for the eaſier performance of their Duties.</p>
            <p>Collection Entries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Raſtall; fol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Cokes</hi> Book of Entries.</p>
            <p>—His Commentary on <hi>Littleton,</hi> being the firſt part of the <hi>Inſtitutes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—His Commentary on <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> &amp;c. or the ſecond Part of the <hi>Inſtitutes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—His Pleas of the Crown, or third Part of the <hi>Inſtitutes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—His Juriſdiction of Courts, or fourth Part of the <hi>Inſtitutes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:60812:8"/>
—His 11 Reports in <hi>French,</hi> with a Table, and the twelfth and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth in <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Abridgment of Caſes, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of Law, contained as well in the Law-Books, Statutes and Records, as of modern Judgments in the Courts of <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi> By <hi>H. Roll,</hi> Serjeant at Law: Publiſhed by the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Hales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Year Books, in 10 Volumes, the laſt Edition, with new Notes and Tables to them all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Origines Juridiciales;</hi> or an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Laws, Courts of Juſtice, Forms of Tryal, Puniſhment in Caſes Criminal, Law-Writers, Law-Books, Grants and Settlements of Eſtates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Alſo a Chronology of the Lord Chancellors, Keepers, Treaſurers, Juſtices Itinerant, Judges, Barons, Maſters of the Rolls, Kings Attorneys, and Sollicitors and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeants at Law. By Sir <hi>William Dug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale</hi> Knight.</p>
            <p>Tables to moſt of the printed Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents of Pleadings, Writs and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of Writs at the Common-Law. Collected by <hi>George Townſend.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="act">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60812:8"/>
            <head>Anno XXII. Caroli II. Regis.</head>
            <head type="sub">An Act to Prevent and Suppreſs Seditious Conventicles.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR Providing far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and moré ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Remedies againſt the growing and dangerous Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Seditious Sectaries, and other Diſloyal Perſons, who under pretence of tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, have or may at their Meetings Contrive Inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, (as late Experience hath ſhewn) Be it Enacted by the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60812:9"/>Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty, by and with the Advice and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons in this preſent Parliament Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled, and by Authority of the ſame, That if any Perſon of the age of Sixteen years or upwards, being a Subject of this Realm, at any time after the tenth day of <hi>May</hi> next, ſhall be preſent at any Aſſembly, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle or Meeting under Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour or Pretence of any Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of Religion, in other man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner than according to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in any place with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> or Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> at which Conventicle, Meeting, or Aſſembly, there ſhall be Five Perſons or more aſſembled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, over and beſides thoſe of the ſame Houſhold, if it be in a Houſe where there is a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60812:9"/>Inhabiting, or if it be in a Houſe, Field, or Place where there is no Family Inhabiting: Then where any five Perſons or more, are ſo Aſſembled as aforeſaid, It ſhall and may be lawfull to and for any one or more Iuſtices of the Peace of the County, Limir, Diviſion, Corporation or Liberty, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Offence aforeſaid ſhall be committed, or for the chief Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate of the Place where ſuch Offence aforeſaid ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; And he and they are hereby Required and Enjoyned, upon Proof to him or them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively made of ſuch Offence, either by Confeſſion of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or Oath of Two Witneſſes (which Oath the ſaid Iuſtice and Iuſtices of the Peace, and Chief Magiſtrate reſpectively, are hereby Impowered and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to Adminiſter) or by no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rorious Evidence and Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60812:10"/>of the Fact, to make a Record of every ſuch Offence under his or their Hands and Seals reſpectively: which Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord ſo made as aforeſaid, ſhall to all intents and purpoſes be in Law taken and adjudged to be a full and perfect Conviction of every ſuch Offender for ſuch Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; and thereupon the ſaid Iuſtice, Iuſtices and chief Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate reſpectively, ſhall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe on every ſuch Offender ſo convict as aforeſaid, a Fine of Five ſhillings for ſuch firſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, which Record and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction ſhall be certified by the ſaid Iuſtice, Iuſtices or chief Magiſtrate at the next Quarter Seſſions of the Peace, for the County or place where the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence was committed.</p>
            <p>And be it farther Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That if ſuch Offender ſo Convicted as aforeſaid, ſhall at any time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60812:10"/>commit the like Offence or Offences, contrary to this Act, and be thereof in manner afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Convicted; Then ſuch Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender ſo convict of ſuch like of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence or offences, ſhall for every ſuch offence incur the Penalty of Ten Shillings, which Fine and Fines, for the firſt and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry other offence, ſhall be levied by Diſtreſs and ſale of the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders Goods and Chattels; or in caſe of the Poverty of ſuch Offender, upon the Goods and Chattels of any other perſon or perſons, who ſhall be then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed in manner aforeſaid of the like Offence at the ſame Conventicle, at the diſcretion of the ſaid Iuſtice, Iuſtices or chief Magiſtrate reſpectively, ſo as the Sum to be levied on any one perſon in caſe of the poverty of other Offenders, amount not in the whole to above the Sum of Ten pounds, upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60812:11"/>of any one Meeting as aforeſaid. And every Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Head-borough, Tything<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Church-wardens, and Overſeers of the Poor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively, are hereby Authorized and reauired to levy the ſame accordingly, having firſt recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a Warrant under the hands of the ſald Iuſtice, Iuſtices or thief Magiſtrate reſpectively ſo to do; the ſaid moneys ſo to be levied, to be forthwith delivered to the ſame Iuſtice, Iuſtices or chief Magiſtrate, and by him or them to be diſtributed; The one third part thereof to the uſe of the Kings Majeſty, his Heirs and Succeſſours, to be paid to the High Sherift of the County for the time being, in manner following; That is to ſay, The Iuſtice or Iuſtices of Peace ſhall pay the ſame into the Court of the reſpective Quarter Seſſions, which ſaid Court
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60812:11"/>ſhall deliver the ſame to the Sheriff, and make a Memorial on Record, of the payment and delivery thereof, which ſaid Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial ſhall be a ſufficient and final Diſcharge to the ſaid Iuſtice and Iuſtices, and a Charge to the Sheriff, which ſaid Diſcharge and Charge, ſhall be certified into the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer together, and not one without the other: And no Iuſtice ſhall or may be queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or accountable for the ſame in the Exchequer, or elſewhere, than in Quarter Seſſions; Another third part thereof to and for the uſe of the Poor of the Pariſh where ſuch Offence ſhall be committed; And the other third part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to the Informer and Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, and to ſuch perſon and perſons as the ſaid Iuſtice, Iuſtices, or chief Magiſtrate reſpectively ſhall appoint, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60812:12"/>regard to their diligence and induſtry in the diſcovery, diſperſing and puniſhing of the ſaid Conventicles.</p>
            <p>And be it farther Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That every perſon who ſhall take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him to Preach or Teach in any ſuch Meeting, Aſſembly, or Conventicle, and ſhall thereof be Convicted as aforeſaid, ſhall forfeit for every ſuch firſt Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, the Sum of Twenty pounds, to be levied in manner aforeſaid, upon his Goods and Chattels; and if the ſaid Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher or Teacher ſo Convicted, be a Stranger, and his Name and Habitation not known, or is fled, add cannot be found, or in the Iudgment of the Iuſtice, Iuſtices or chief Magiſtrate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom he ſhall be Convicted, ſhall be thought unable to pay the ſame, the ſaid Iuſtice, Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces or chief Magiſtrate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60812:12"/>are hereby Impowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and Required to levy the ſame by Warrant as aforeſaid, upon the Goods and Chattels of any ſuch Perſons who ſhall be preſent at the ſame Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle; Any thing in this or any other Act, Law or Statute to the contrary notwithſtanding. And the money ſo levied, to be diſpoſed of in manner aforeſaid: And if ſuch Offender ſo Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed as aforeſaid, ſhall at any time again commit the like Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence or Offences contrary to this Act, and be thereof Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed in manner aforeſaid, then ſuch Offender ſo Convicted of ſuch like Offence or Offences, ſhall for every ſuch Offence, incur the Penalty of Forty pounds, to be levied and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>And be it farther Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That every perſon who ſhall witting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60812:13"/>and willingly ſuffer any ſuch Conventicle, Meeting, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull Aſſembly aforeſaid, to be held in his or her Houſe, Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, Barn, Yard, or Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, and be Convicted thereof in manner aforeſaid, ſhall forfeit the Sum of Twenty pounds, to be levied in manner aforeſaid, upon his or her Goods and Chattels; or in caſe of his or her poverty or inability as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, upon the Goods and Chattels of ſuch perſons who ſhall be Convicted in manner a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid of being preſent at the ſame Conventicle; and the Money ſo levied, to be diſpoſed of in manner aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Provided alwaies, and be it Enacted by the Authority afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, That no perſon ſhall by any Clauſe of this Act, be lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to pay above Ten pounds for any one Meeting, in regard of the poverty of any other perſon or perſons.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:60812:13"/>
Provided alſo, and be it far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Enacted, That in all caſes of this Act, where the Penalty or Sum charged upon any Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender, exceeds the Sum of Ten ſhillings, and ſuch Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſhall find himſelf agrieved, it ſhall and may be lawfull for him within one week after the ſaid Penalty or Maney charged, ſhall be paid or levied, to Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal in writing from the perſon or perſons Convicting, to the Iudgment of the Iuſtices of the Peace in their next Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Seſſions; to whom the Iuſtice or Iuſtices of Peace, Chief Magiſtrate, or Alderman, that firſt convicted ſuch Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ſhall return the Money le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied upon the Appellant, and ſhall certifie under his and their Hands and Seals, the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence upon which the Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on paſt with the whole Record thereof, and the ſaid Appeal:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60812:14"/>Whereupon ſuch Offender may Plead and make Defence, and have his Tryal by a Iury there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon: And in caſe ſuch Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellant ſhall not Proſecute with effect, or if upon ſuch Tryal he ſhall not be acquitted, or Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment paſs not for him upon his ſaid Appeal, the ſaid Iuſtices at the Seſſions, ſhall give treble coſts againſt ſuch Offender for his unjuſt Appeal: And no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Court whatſoever ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termeddle with any Cauſe or Cauſes of Appeal upon this Act, but they ſhall be finally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined in the Quarter Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons onely.</p>
            <p>Provided alwaies, and be it farther Enacted, That upon the delivery of ſuch Appeal, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, the perſon or perſons Appellant ſhall enter before the perſon or perſons convicting, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Recognizance, to proſecute the ſaid Appeal with effect:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60812:14"/>Which ſaid Recognizance, the perſon or perſons Convicting, is hereby Impowered to take, and required to certifie the ſame to the next Quarter Seſſions: And in caſe no ſuch Recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance be entred into, the ſaid Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to be null and void.</p>
            <p>Provided alwaies, That eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuch Appeal ſhall be left with the perſon or perſons ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victing, as aforeſaid, at the time of the making thereof.</p>
            <p>And be it farther Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That the Iuſtice, Iuſtices of the Peace, and chief Magiſtrate reſpectively, or the reſpective Conſtables, Headboroughs, and Tything-men, by Warrant from the ſaid Iuſtice, Iuſtices, or chief Magiſtrare reſpectively, ſhall and may with what aid, force and aſſiſtance they ſhall think fit, for the better Execution of this Act, after refuſal or denial
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60812:15"/>to enter, break open, and enter into any houſe or other place, where they ſhall be informed any ſuch Conventicle as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid is or ſhall be held, as well within Liberries as without; and take into their Cuſtody the perſons there unlawfully aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, to the intent they may be proceeded againſt according to this Act: And that the Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, or Deputy-Lieutenants, or any Commiſſionated Officer of the Militia, or other of his Majeſties Forces, with ſuch Troops or Companies of Horſe and Foot: And alſo the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs and other Magiſtrates and Miniſters of Iuſtice, or any of them jointly, or ſeverally, within any the Counties or pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces within this Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> or Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> with ſuch other aſſiſtance as they ſhall think meet, or can
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60812:15"/>get in readineſs with the ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, on Certificate made to them reſpectively under the Hand and Seal of any one Iuſtice of the Peace, or chief Magiſtrate, of his particular Information or Knowledge of ſuch unlawfull Meeting or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle held, or to be held in their reſpective Counties or Places; And that he with ſuch Aſſiſtance as he can get toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is not able to ſuppreſs and diſſolve the ſame, ſhall and may, and are hereby required and enjoyned to repair unto the place where they are ſo held, or to be held, and by the beſt means they can, to diſſolve, diſſipate, or prevent all ſuch unlawfull Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, and take into their Cuſts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſuch and ſo many of the ſaid perſons ſo unlawfully Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, as they ſhall think fit, to the intent they may be procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt according to this Act.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:60812:16"/>
Provided always, That no Dwelling-houſe of any Peer of this Realm, where he or his Wife ſhall be then reſident, ſhall be ſearched by virtue of this Act, but by immediate War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant from His Majeſty, under His Sign Manual; or in the preſence of the Lieutenant, or one Deputy-Lieutenant, or two Iuſtices of the Peace, whereof one to be of the <hi>Quorum</hi> of the ſame County or Riding.</p>
            <p>And be it farther Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That if any Conſtable, Head-borough, Tything-man, Church-warden, or Overſeer of the Poor, who ſhall know, or be credibly infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of any ſuch Meetings or Conventicles held within his Precincts, Pariſh or Limits, and ſhall not give Information thereof to ſome Iuſtice of the Peace, or the chief Magiſtrate, and endeavour the Conviction
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60812:16"/>of the Parties, according to his Duty; but ſuch Conſtable, Head-borough, Tything-man, Church-warden, Overſeers of the Poor, or any perſon law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully called in and of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, Head-borough or Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing-man, ſhall willfully and wittingly omit the performance of his Duty, in the Execution of this Act, and he thereof Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed in manner aforeſaid, he ſhall forfeit for every ſuch Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, the ſum of five pounds, to de levied upon his Goods and Chattels, and diſpoſed in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner aforeſaid: And that if any Iuſtice of the Peace, or chief Magiſtrate, ſhall wilfully and wittingly omit the performance of his Duty in the Execution of this Act, he ſhall forfeit the ſum of One hundred pounds, the one moiety to the uſe of his Majeſty, the other moiety to the uſe of the Informer, to be
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60812:17"/>recovered by Action, Suit, Bill or Plaint, in any of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> wherein no Eſſoin, Protection, or Wager of Law ſhall lie.</p>
            <p>And be it farther Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That if any perſon be at any time Sued for putting in Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution any of the Powers contained in this Act, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than upon Appeal al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by this Act, ſuch perſon ſhall and may plead the General Iſſue, and give the ſpecial mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in Evidente; and if the Plaintiff be Non-ſuit, or a Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict paſs for the Defendant, or if the Plaintiff diſcontinue his Action, or if upon Demurrer, Iudgment be given for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant, every ſuch Defendant ſhall have his full treble Coſts.</p>
            <p>And be it farther Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That this Act, and all Clauſes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60812:17"/>contained, ſhall be conſtrued moſt largely and beneficially for the ſuppreſſing of Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, and for the Iuſtification and Encouragement of all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to be imployed in the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution thereof; And that no Record, Warrant, or <hi>Mittimus</hi> to be made by virtue of this Act, or any Proceedings there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, ſhall be Reverſed, Avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, or any way Impeached by reaſon of any Default in form. And in caſe any perſon offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding againſt this Act, ſhall be an Inhabitant in any other County or Corporation, or flie into any other County or Corporation, after the Offence committed, the Iuſtice of the Peace, or chief Magiſtrate, before whom he ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed as aforeſaid, ſhall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the ſame under his hand and ſeal, to any Iuſtice of Peace, or chief Magiſtrate of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:60812:18"/>ſuch other County or Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion wherein the ſaid perſon or perſons are Inhabitants, or are fled into; whith ſaid Iuſtice or chief Magiſtrate reſpectively, is hereby Authorized and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to levy the Penalty or Penalties in this Act mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, upon the Goods and Chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels of ſuch perſon or perſons, as ſully as the ſaid other Iuſtice of Peace might have done, in caſe he or they had been Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants in the place where the Offence was committed.</p>
            <p>Provided alſo, That no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhall be puniſhed for any Offence againſt this Act, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſuch Offender be proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the ſame within Three months after the offence com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. And that no perſon who ſhall be puniſhed for any offence by virtue of this Act, ſhall be puniſhed for the ſame offence by virtue of any other Act or Law whatſoever.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:60812:18"/>
Provided, and be it farther Enacted by the Authority afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, That every Alderman of <hi>London</hi> for the time being, within the City of <hi>London,</hi> and the Liverties thereof, ſhall have (and they and every of them are hereby Impowered and Required to Execute) the ſame Power and Authority within <hi>London,</hi> and the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries thereof, for the Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Convicting, and Puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of all offences within this Act committed within <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and the Liberries thereof, which any Iuſtice of Peace hath by this Act in any County of <hi>England,</hi> and ſhall be ſubject to the ſame Penalties and Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, for not doing that which by this Act is directed to be done by any Iuſtice of Peace in any County of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Provided, and be it Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60812:19"/>if the perſon offending and Convicted as aforeſaid, be a Feme-Covert, cohabiting with her Husband, the Penalties of Five ſhillings, and Ten ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, ſo as aforeſaid incurred, ſhall be levied by Warrant, as aforeſaid, upon the Goods and Chattels of the Husband of ſuch Feme-Covert.</p>
            <p>Provided alſo, That no Peer of this Realm ſhall be Atta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched or Impriſoned by virtue or force of this Act; Any thing, Matter or Clauſe therein to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Provided alſo, That neither this Act, nor any thing therein contained, ſhall extend to inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidate or avoid His Majeſties Supremacy in Eccleſiaſtical affairs; but that His Majeſty, and His Heirs and Succeſſors may from time to time, and at all times hereafter, Exerciſe and enjoy all Powers and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60812:19"/>in Eccleſiaſtical Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, as fully and as amply as Himſelf or any of His Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors have or might have done the ſame: Any thing in this Act notwithſtanding.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="observations">
            <pb facs="tcp:60812:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60812:20"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Some Obſervations upon the Statute of</hi> 22 Car. Secundi, Cap. 1. <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>An Act to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent and ſuppreſs Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious Conventicles.</hi>
               </hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 1.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FOR providing far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and more ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Remedies,</hi> &amp;c. Beſides the Statute of 16 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. which is, and at the time of making this Act was expired. there were ſeveral other Acts yet in force, for the preventing and ſuppreſſing of Seditious Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, as the Statute of 35 <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 1. Entituled, <hi>An Act to Retain the Queens Majeſty's Subjects
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60812:21"/>in their due Obedience;</hi> which Act being but Temporary at firſt by the Statute of 39 <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 18. was continued to the end of the next Parliament, and by the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of 43 <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 9. was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued to the end of the firſt Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the next Parliament. And by the Statute of 1 <hi>Jacobi, cap.</hi> 25. was continued untill the end of the firſt Seſſion of the next Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The ſame Parliament of 1 <hi>Jacobi,</hi> continued by ſeveral Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogations in 3, 4, and 7 <hi>Jacobi,</hi> ſo that the next Parliament after the continuance of 1 <hi>Jacobi,</hi> was hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in 18 <hi>Jac.</hi> where only two Bills of Subſidies paſt, and nothing more was done in that Parliament; whereupon in 20 <hi>Jac.</hi> it came to be a Queſtion whether this Act of 35 were in force, or not, as appears in <hi>Huttons Rep.</hi> fol. 61. The Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es being in doubt as it ſeems, by reaſon of a Proviſo in the Bills of Subſidies, that the Royal Aſſent to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60812:21"/>theſe Bills ſhould not determine that Seſſion of Parliament, which doubtleſs it did not; yet when the Parliament was afterwards Diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and nothing more done;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Co.</hi> 4. <hi>Inſt.</hi> 27.28.</note> The paſſing of theſe two Bills being matter of Record, made it ſuch a Seſſion of the next Parliament that diſcontinued this Act of 35 <hi>Eliz.</hi> But to prevent the doubt after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards by the Statute of 21 <hi>Jacobi, cap.</hi> 27. It was Enacted that ſo much of the ſaid Act of 35 <hi>Eliz.</hi> as hath not been ſince Repealed by any other Statute, ſhall be adjudged ever ſince the Seſſion of Parliament in 7 <hi>Jacobi,</hi> to have been of ſuch force and effect, as the ſame was the laſt day of that Seſſion. And from thenceforth untill the end of the firſt Seſſion of the next Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which next Parliament was in 1 <hi>Car. Primi.</hi> And at the end of that Parliament, this Statute of 39 <hi>Eliz.</hi> was again diſcontinued,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60812:22"/>but by the Statute of 3 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. the Statute of 35 <hi>Eliz. viz.</hi> ſo much of it as hath not been Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed by any other Statute, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued to the end of the firſt Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the next Parliament in ſuch force and effect, as it was on the firſt day of the Seſſion of Parliament holden in <hi>An.</hi> 1 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the Statute of 16 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. in the cloſe of a Tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Act, Entituled, <hi>An Act for the farther Relief of His Majeſty's Army, and the Northern parts of the Kingdom.</hi> All Statutes and Acts of Parliament (whereof the Act of 35 <hi>Eliz.</hi> is one) which have their continuance, or were by the Act of 3 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. made, are Enacted to have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance untill ſome other Act of Parliament be made touching the continuance or diſcontinuance of the ſame, by which laſt Act the Statute of 35 <hi>Eliz.</hi> is made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual; there having been no Act
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60812:22"/>ſince made either for the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, or diſcontinuance of the ſame. But yet there remains one Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon it ſtill, <hi>viz.</hi> why the Acts of 21 <hi>Jac.</hi> and 3 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. do not continue this Act of 35 <hi>Eliz.</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally, but only ſo much of it as was unrepealed by any former Act. To this it is anſwered; That in the Act of 35 <hi>Eliz.</hi> there are two Clauſes, being the <hi>8th</hi> and <hi>9th</hi> Paragraphs on Mr. <hi>Keebles</hi> Statute Book, the firſt, For impoſing a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty upon ſuch Perſons as ſhould harbour or entertain in their Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes any Perſon, which ſhould obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately refuſe to repair to Divine Service by a Month. And the next Clauſe being a Proviſo, That the Law ſhould not extend to the harbouring of a Wife and other Relations there named, are both Repealed by the Statute of 3 <hi>Jac. cap.</hi> 4. which was the reaſon that the Statute of 35 <hi>Eliz.</hi> was not wholly continued, but only ſo
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60812:23"/>much as was Unrepealed, which is the whole Statute, ſave only theſe two Clauſes.</p>
               <p>I have been the longer about this Act of 35 <hi>Eliz.</hi> to prove it in Force at this day: for that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Judgment of the whole Parliament that it is in Force declared in the expired Act of 16 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. by which every Man ought to be concluded in point of Law; it hath often been affirmed to me, that the Act of 35 <hi>Eliz.</hi> was diſcontinued, and not now in Force: but ſuch Affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation rather proceeded from af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to have it ſo, than from any other Ground.</p>
               <p>The Statute of 23 <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 1. againſt ſaying and hearing of Maſs.</p>
               <p>The Statute of 13 and 14 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> againſt Quakers.</p>
               <p>The Statute of 13 and 14 <hi>Car.</hi> 2 <hi>cap.</hi> 4. for Uniformity of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Prayers.</p>
               <p>The Statute of 17 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60812:23"/>commonly called the <hi>Oxford</hi> Act, for Reſtraining of Nonconformiſts from Inhabiting in Corporations. All which Statutes, and ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers did in part provide Remedies againſt the Seditious Practices of Sectaries, and Diſloyal Perſons. And this Act provideth farther and more ſpeedy Remedies againſt them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>That is any Perſon,</hi> &amp;c. This word <hi>Perſon</hi> extends both to Men and Women. See the <hi>16th</hi> Paragraph of this Act, <hi>And to Peers as well as Commoners.</hi> But Peers are not to be Arreſted or Impriſon'd, as Commoners may be. See the <hi>17th</hi> Paragraph here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>under. <hi>So a Iuſtice of Peace, or Mayor, or other head Officer, being dofuntarily preſent at a Conventirle, for any other Cauſe, except for the ſuppreſſing of it, may, and ought to be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dviued as an Oſtendes within this Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:60812:24"/>
3. <hi>Of the Age of</hi> 16 <hi>years or upwards,</hi> &amp;c. This is plain, and if Evidence be given againſt a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for being preſent at a Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, who is of the growth, or ſtature of a young Man, or young Woman, it is to be intended that ſuch Perſon is of the Age of 16 years, unleſs the contrary be ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially made appear. And in ſuch Caſe the proof, or <hi>Onus probandi,</hi> reſts upon the Offender in ſuch Convictions, whereupon there lies an Appeal by this Act, and ſo I take it to be likewiſe where the Offender is Perſonally Convented at the time of his Conviction, and objects not his Nonage to prevent his Conviction. But if one be Convicted as an Offender when abſent, from which Conviction no Appeal is given by this Act, as where the Penalty is only 5 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> or 10 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> There, it may be the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction will be utterly void, and the Offender may maintain an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60812:24"/>of Treſpaſs againſt the Officer that Levies the Penalty of 5 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> or 10 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> upon his Goods, for that he hath no other Remedy to help him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. And therefore if the Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der be preſent, when Convicted, it will be the ſafeſt way to mention it in the Record.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Being a Subject of this Realm,</hi> &amp;c. The word <hi>(being)</hi> relates to the time of the Offence to be committed, and not to the time of paſſing the Act; for if an Alien at the time of the Act paſſed, were afterwards Naturalized, and afterwards be preſent at a Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, he is within the word, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Subject,</hi> &amp;c. Though he were not a Subject of this Realm at the time of the Act paſſed. It is next to be conſidered, who ſhall be ſaid to be (or rather not to be) a Subject of this Realm, within the meaning of the Act, for all men within the Realm are Subjects to the King, either (1.) By Birth, as born in <hi>England,</hi> or any other of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60812:25"/>the King's Dominions. (2.) By Naturalization, as where an Act of Parliament of <hi>England</hi> gives an Alien the ſame Privileges that a Subject born hath, by reaſon of his Birth. (3.) By Denization by the King's Letters Patents, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by an Alien is made a free Denizen to purchaſe Lands, and to hold them to him and his Heirs, which an Alien cannot do, or, (4.) By reſiding, or being in <hi>England,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the King's Protection, as Aliens are, which makes them Subjects to the King of <hi>England,</hi> ſo long as they remain in any part of his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, but no longer. But the word, <hi>Subjects of this Realm,</hi> in the Act intends a diſtinction, that ſome Perſons Inhabiting within the Realm, ſhould not be comprehended within the Law. And therefore by theſe words all Natural Subjects born in any of the Kings Dominions. All Perſons, that by Act of Parliament of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:60812:25"/>are Naturalized Subjects, and all Perſons Endenized by the King's Letters Patents under the great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended within the Law (I mean) are to undergo the Penalty of the Law, for being preſent at a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle. But Aliens reſident in <hi>England,</hi> and thoſe that are Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralized, or Endenized in <hi>Scotland.</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> and not in <hi>England,</hi> and ſo continue ſtill as Aliens in <hi>England,</hi> are not within this Law, nor ſhall they be puniſhed by it. Now in this Caſe, as well as in the Caſe of Infancy, under the Age of 16 years, the proof reſts upon the Offender, for every one in this Caſe ſhall be preſumed to be a Natural Subject of this Realm, unleſs the contrary be made appear. And the Conviction will be of the ſame effect againſt an Alien, as it is above declared to be againſt an Infant; only this I conceive fit to add, that if an Infant under 16, or
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60812:26"/>an Alien, having been preſent at a Conventicle, be ſummoned to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before the Juſtice of Peace, or chief Magiſtrate, to ſhew Cauſe why he ſhould not be Convicted for ſuch offence, and refuſeth, or neglecteth to appear, and make his defence, and thereupon he is Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed; I take ſuch Conviction to be binding, and the Infant, or A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lien ſhall never avoid it, and the rather, by reaſon of the firſt part of the <hi>13th</hi> Paragraph of this Act.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Shall be preſent at any Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, Conventicle, or Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> &amp;c. Yet every one that is preſent (though a Subject of the Realm, above the Age of 16) ſhall not be puniſhed as an Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der within this Law. For (1.) One that is an Idiot, or a Lunatick, <q>(unleſs it be during ſome lucid interval, wherein he enjoys the uſe of his reaſon, ſo far as to be ſuppoſed knowing of what he does)</q> though preſent at a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60812:26"/>yet cannot be ſaid to be preſent, under colour, or pretence of Exerciſe of Religion. (2.) One that is Impriſon'd, and kept at a Conventicle againſt his Will. For <hi>Actus non facit reum niſi mens ſit rea;</hi> the like may be ſaid of him that is under a Terrour of Bodily harm, by reaſon of Threats or Menaces of others, which he could not otherwiſe avoid, but by being preſent; but if a Servant by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of his Maſter, or a Wife by Command of her Husband, be preſent, this will not excuſe them, becauſe they might, (without the Guilt of Diſobedience) have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to obey ſuch Command; what if the Husband enforce his Wife, co-habiting with him, to be preſent at a Conventicle againſt her Will, whether is ſhe to be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed or not? In this particular Caſe I conceive ſhe is; for by the <hi>16th</hi> Paragraph of this Act, the Penalties of 5 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> and 10 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> are to be
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60812:27"/>Levied upon the Goods of the Husband. And ſo the Wifes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſent at a Conventicle, is within the Letter, and the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Husband is within the meaning of the Act. If one be preſent at a Conventicle, to the end to detect, and diſcover the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle, and to give Evidence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Offenders, in order to their Conviction, he is not an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender within this Law; but he that is preſent at a Conventicle, out of Curioſity to obſerve what they ſay or do, he is an Offender againſt this Law, and ought to be Convicted as well as any other.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Vnder Colour, or pretence of any Exerciſe of Religion,</hi> &amp;c. The Preamble of this Statute ſaith, <hi>That Seditious Sectaries, and other Diſloyal Perſons, under pretence of tender Can ſciences, at their Meetings contrive In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrections.</hi> And thoſe Meetings were, and are commonly under
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60812:27"/>Colour, or pretence of Exerciſe of Religion. Now if there be a Meeting of Sectaries, of the number of 5, or upwards, above the Houſhold, or of five, or upwards, where there is no Houſhold; but before they proceed to any pretended Exerciſe of Religion, they are diſturbed, and ſuppreſſed, the Queſtion is, whether theſe, or any of them may be Convicted for being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at a Conventicle, under Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, or Pretence of any Exerciſe of Religion, ſeeing none was there Exerciſed? This is a Queſtion that may, and I ſuppoſe doth often hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, and I take it ſomewhat clear, that in ſuch Caſe they may, and ought to be Convicted; For the chief end and deſign of that Statute was to prevent Sedition and Inſurrections, and as a means to obtain that end, this Law is made to ſuppreſs Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticies, where (as the Statute takes notice) Sedition and Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections were contrived. Now if
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60812:28"/>they ſhould not be Convicted, though there was no actual Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of Religion, then their Plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Sedition, and contriving In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrections being the greater Evil, ſhould eſcape Correction, whilſt a pretended Exerciſe of Religion being the leſſer Evil, as being but in order to the greater Evil of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and Inſurrections, ſhould be puniſhed, which is not, nor could be the intent of the Statute; for in my Apprehenſion, the Statute meant, to puniſh all thoſe that ſhould meet together under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Exerciſe of Religion, though none were actually Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed; for that it is the ſame, or a worſe miſchief, than if there were any Exerciſe of Religion.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>In other manner than ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Liturgy and Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> What the Liturgy and Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is, appears by the Act of Uniformity
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60812:28"/>of 13 &amp; 14 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. which is commonly printed before the Service Book, or Book of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer; ſo where there is any Exerciſe of Religion in Publick, that is, where five, or more be met together, beſides thoſe of the ſame Houſhold, there, if the Prayers in the Service Book be not uſed, and directions of that Book obſerved, that is an Exerciſe of Religion in other manner than according to the Liturgy, and Practice of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> But it may be Objected that the Service Book hath appointed the Form of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Prayers and Adminiſtration of the Sacraments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But hath not appointed any Order to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in Preaching, and therefore Preaching in a Conventicle cannot be ſaid to be in other manner than according to the Liturgy and Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> there being no manner appointed by the Liturgy for Preaching. To
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60812:29"/>To this it is anſwered; that by the <hi>22d</hi> Paragraph or Section of the Act of Uniformity, it is Enacted, <hi>That at all and every time and times, when any Sermon or Leaure is to he Preached, the Common Prayers and Service in and by the ſaid Book</hi> (viz. <hi>the Book of Common-Prayer, appointed to be read for that time of the day) ſhall be openly, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly, and ſolemnly read by ſome Prieſt, or Deacon in the Church, Chapel, or place of publick Worſhip, where the ſaid Sermon or Lecture is to be Preached before ſuch Sermon or Lecture be Preached, and that the Lecturer then to Preach ſhall be preſent at the reading thereof.</hi> So that Preaching in a Conventicle, where the Common Prayers appointed to be read for the time of the day are not firſt ſolemnly read, is an Exerciſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in other manner than accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60812:29"/>to the Liturgy and Practice of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and an Offence againſt this Statute.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>In any place within the Kingdom of</hi> England, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe words are plain, and therefore if there be an Aſſembly or Meeting in a Church by five Perſons or more, under pretence of any Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Religion in other manner than according to the Liturgy and Practice of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> the ſame is a Conventicle within this Act, where any one, or more preſent, who is of the Age of 16, or upwards, and a Subject of this Realm, ought to be Convicted. But this is not to be underſtood of Foreigners, and Aliens of the Foreign Reformed Churches, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, or to be allowed by His Majeſty, his Heirs, or Succeſſours in <hi>England;</hi> for the Act of Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity (which this was made to ſtrengthen) doth not extend to them, as by the Proviſo in the <hi>15th</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:60812:30"/>Paragraph of that Act appeareth, and which Prerogative of allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to ſuch Foreigners, or Aliens Churches is ſaved to His Majeſty by the laſt Paragraph in this Act.</p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>At which Conventicle, Meeting, or Aſſembly, there ſhall be five Perſons or more Aſſembled together over and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thoſe of the ſame Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold, if it be in a Houſe where there is a Family Inhabiting, or if it be in a Houſe, Field, or Place where there is no Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Inhabiting, then where any five or more are ſo Aſſembled as aforeſaid, then,</hi> &amp;c. Now are we come to a complete definition of a Conventicle within this Act, which is, <hi>where five or more</hi> where there is no Houſhold are met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther under Colour or pretence of any Exerciſe of Religion in other manner than according to the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy and Practice of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> wherein theſe things
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:60812:30"/>are to be obſerved, (1.) That the Perſon or Perſons that are to be puniſhed by this Law, for being preſent at a Conventicle, muſt be of the Age of 16, or upwards, and a Subject of this Realm. (2.) That though the Perſon to be puniſhed, muſt have theſe Qualifications, yet Aliens (or Minors) if they are of diſcretion, may make up the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of five, to make it a Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle within this Law; as for Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, ſuppoſe five are met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a Houſe, beſides the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold, under Colour and pretence of Exerciſe of Religion in other manner than according to the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and four of thoſe are Aliens, and the fifth a Subject of the Age of 16, this is nevertheleſs a Conventicle, though four of the five cannot be puniſhed, as being Aliens, yet the fifth being a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, ſhall be Convicted and puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by this Law for being preſent at ſuch Conventicle; for the Law
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60812:31"/>deſcribes him that is to be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed, to be of the Age of 16, or upwards, and a Subject of this Realm; but the Conventicle at which he was preſent, and for which he is Convicted, is only to be a Meeting together, or an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of five, or more Perſons, whether Aliens, or Subjects, is all one. (3.) That where there is a Meeting in a Houſe of five Perſons, or above, beſides thoſe of the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold, and ſo a Conventicle; there thoſe of the ſame Houſhold, if pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at the Conventicle, being of the Age of 16, and Subjects of this Realm may and ought to be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed for being at the Conventicle, as well as any others. I think by the word Houſhold, both Lodgers and Inmates are included; ſo that there muſt be five over and above the Houſhold, and the Lodgers and Inmates as part of the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold. (4.) The Preacher or Teacher in ſuch Conventicles,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60812:31"/>though an Alien, or not of the Age of 16, ought to be Convicted. See the third Paragraph of this Act. (5.) If a Subject of the Age of 16, or upwards, be preſent at the Church or Aſſembly of Foreigners or Aliens of the Foreign Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches allowed by His Majeſty, he is not to be Convicted for being at a Conventicle, for ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Aſſembly it ſelf is Lawfull, he that is preſent at it cannot be ſaid to have committed an Offence within this Act.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Then where any five Perſons or more are ſo Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, as aforeſaid, it ſhall and may be Lawfull to, and for any one or more Iuſtices of the Peace of the County, Limit, Diviſion, Corporation or Liberty wherein the Offence aforeſaid ſhall be committed, or for the chief Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate of the Place, where the Offence aforeſaid ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and he and they are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60812:32"/>required,</hi> &amp;c. By this Clauſe are the Magiſtrates deſcribed that have Authority, and ought to Convict Offenders for being at Conventicles, which are one or more Juſtices of the Peace of the County (that is, where there are Juſtices of the Peace of the whole County, as there are in moſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in <hi>England</hi>) Limit, as in <hi>Lincoln<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> where there are two Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions of the Peace, one for the parts of <hi>Holland,</hi> and another for the parts of <hi>Keſteven</hi> Diviſion; as in <hi>Torkſhire,</hi> where there are three Diviſions, namely, the Eaſt-Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, the Weſt-Riding, and the North-Riding, and a ſeveral Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the Peace for each of thoſe three Diviſions; (Corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) as <hi>London, York, Briſtol,</hi> and others that are Counties of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and wherein the Juſtices of Peace for the County at large, have nothing to do, or elſe ſuch Corporations that continue parcel
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60812:32"/>of the County at large, yet have Juſtices of their own exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive to the Juſtices of the Peace of the County where the Corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, ſo that the Juſtices of the County may not intermeddle. And laſtly, Liberties which have Juſtices of Peace within the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and yet the Juſtices of the County or Riding where ſuch Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties have a concurrent Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction. Now if where the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence happens, be ſuch a Liberty that the Juſtices of the County at large may not intermeddle; then the Juſtice or Juſtices of Peace of ſuch Liberty are only bound to Convict the Offender; but if the Offence happens in a Corporation, or Liberty where the Juſtices of the County have a concurrent Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction with the Juſtices of the Liberty, there both the Juſtices of the County, as well as the Juſtices of the Liberty, are bound upon Notice to Convict the Offenders.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60812:33"/>Now what if the chief Magiſtrate, and one or more Juſtices of Peace of the place, ſhould jointly Convict Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders, where the Act ſaith, <hi>That one or more Iuſtices of Peace, or chief Magiſtrate,</hi> is ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction good? I think it may be good enough, however I would not adviſe it as ſafe, becauſe it ſeems prejudicial to the Appeals given by this Act, for it may fall out that all the Juſtices and chief Magiſtrate might Record the firſt Conviction, and the Party grieved would have no Appeal but only to the ſame Perſons who Convicted him, which would be inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent. <q>And yet it ſeems any Juſtice or Juſtices of Peace of the Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration or Liberty, as well as the chief Magiſtrate of the place may make ſuch Conviction, or all together, for though the Appeal ſhould happen to be given to the ſame Perſons who made the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, yet that takes not away
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60812:33"/>the benefit of ſuch Appeal, for beſides the ſuppoſed honour and impartiality of the Magiſtrate making ſuch Conviction, upon the Appeal the Tryal of the Fact is to be by a Jury, whereas the Conviction is by the Opinion and Judgment of the Juſtice or Magiſtrate, and ſo as to the Fact the Party does as it were Appeal to a Jury from the Juſtice. See hereafter, Sect. 6. concerning Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>Vpon proof to him or them reſpectively made of ſuch Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence either by confeſſion of the Party,</hi> &amp;c. This Confeſſion muſt be Judicial before the Juſtice him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf at the time of the Conviction, and not a Confeſſion at another time, or before other Perſons; for ſuch Confeſſion, though ſworn be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Juſtices by ſufficient Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, is only an Evidence, or Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of the Fact, but not a ground to Convict the Offender
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60812:34"/>
                  <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> as a Confeſſion before the Juſtice himſelf is.</p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>Or Dath of two Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,</hi> &amp;c. An Infamous Perſon, as one Convicted of Perjury, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery, or of Felony, and not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had his benefit of the Clergy, nor pardoned, is by Law diſabled to give Teſtimony in any matter or cauſe whatſoever, and therefore cannot be one of the two Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes within this Act, upon whoſe Oath the Offender is to be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed, nor ought to be ſuffered to be ſworn, if the Juſtice know him to be ſuch; but if ſuch Perſon be ſworn, and the Juſtice not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſuch diſability of the Party ſworn, do proceed, and upon ſuch Oath, and upon the Oath of one other Witneſs, doth make a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of Conviction, ſuch Record will be good in Law, and bind, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs (where an Appeal lyeth) it be avoided by Appeal according to the direction of this Act; a Jew
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60812:34"/>hath been often admitted as a Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs by the Judge without the conſent of Parties, and ſworn up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Old Teſtament, and ſo I conceive he may be in this Caſe. A man preſent at a Conventicle, though an Offender himſelf, is queſtionleſs a good Witneſs to give Evidence in order to the Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any other for being preſent at the ſame Conventicle. A Man that is only Indicted of Perjury, or any other Infamous Crime, but not Convicted, is a Witneſs, for no Man is diſabled to give Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony upon Oath upon a bare In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment only; note in this Caſe the Oath of the Witneſſes, and all other Evidence given upon Oath before the Juſtice or Juſtices Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victing, ſhould be put in Writing, and ſubſcribed by the Party ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, or giving ſuch Evidence at the time of his Depoſition or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination, eſpecially where an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal is given by this Act, for that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60812:35"/>by the <hi>6th</hi> Paragraph it is required, <hi>That upon an Appeal the Iuſtice certify to the Seſſions the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence upon which the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction paſt,</hi> which he cannot ſo well nor ſafely do, unleſs the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence be taken in writing and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by the Party upon whoſe Oath the ſame is taken.</p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>Or by Notorious Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and Circumſtance of the Fact,</hi> &amp;c. It is very difficult, if not impoſſible to lay down the exact meaſure or bounds, what ſhall be ſaid to the Notorious Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Circumſtance of the Fact, and what not, and therefore it muſt be left to the Judgment and Diſcretion of the Juſtice, or Juſtices Convicting, upon weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well, and conſidering of the Caſe, what doth appear to be a Notorious Evidence or Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Fact. But this is to be taken notice of particularly, that the proof of two things are
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60812:35"/>principally material. (1.) That there be a Conventicle, and, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, That the Party to be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed, was preſent at it. Now if a Conventicle be kept, and the ſame is afterwards diſperſed, and the Preacher or Teacher in ſuch Conventicle, or the Owner of the Houſe where ſuch Conventicle is held, or ſeveral Perſons preſent at ſuch Conventicle be Convicted for ſuch Offence, afterwards another Perſon by two Witneſſes is proved to have been there, or that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed he was there at the ſame time and place where the others Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed were, but the Witneſſes can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not prove it a Conventicle; yet here's a Notorious Evidence and Circumſtance of the Fact ſufficient to ground a Conviction. If the Juſtice of Peace be preſent at the ſuppreſſing of an Aſſembly of People, ſome of whom are imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately Convented before him, and Accuſed for holding and being at a
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:60812:36"/>Conventicle in ſuch Aſſembly, but no direct proof be made that it was a Conventicle, farther, than that they were Aſſembled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; if the Perſons Convented can or will not give an account for what other Cauſe they were ſo Aſſembled or met together, or if they or ſome others at ſuch Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly are commonly known, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to be frequenters of Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, or that they commonly (though not always) do neglect coming to Church, or have decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, or any way made their diſlike of, or averſion from the Liturgy or Doctrine of the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland:</hi> This is (in any Opinion) ſuch a Notorious Evidence and Circumſtance of the Fact, as is ſufficient to ground a Conviction within the intent of the Law, and in ſuch and the like Caſes the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of Conviction needs not make mention of any thing more, but that the Offender is Convicted
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:60812:36"/>by the Notorious Evidence and Circumſtance of the Fact, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out particularizing the Fact, for that where no Appeal lies, the Juſtice is the ſole Judge of the Notoriety of the Evidence and Circumſtance; and where an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal is given, there the Fact muſt be tryed over again, and ſo the Offender cannot be injured.</p>
               <p n="14">14. <hi>To make a Record of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſuch Offence under his or their Hands and Seals reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively,</hi> &amp;c, For the Form of ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, ſee hereunder. And note, that the ſubſcribing the Juſtices hand to the Record, is abſolutely Eſſential, for though the Juſtice ſet to his Seal, and it be ſo mentioned in the Record (which is as much as the Law requireth in moſt Caſes,) yet this Act requiring the Record to be as well under his Hand as Seal; if it be not under both, the Record, and all that is done in purſuance of it will be altogether
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60812:37"/>void, though it be not of abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute neceſſity that the Record ſhould mention that the Juſtice hath put his Hand and Seal (ſo that it be actually done) but the better and ſafer way is to mention it in the Record according to the Precedent.</p>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>Which Record ſo made as aforeſaid, ſhall to all intents and purpoſes be in Law taken and Adjudged to be a full and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Conviction,</hi> &amp;c. So as the Party Convicted ſhall be conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to ſay that he is not guilty of the Offence contained in ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord he is ſo Convicted.</p>
               <p n="16">16. <hi>And thereupon the ſaid Iuſtice,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſhall impoſe on e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſuch Offender ſo Convict as aforeſaid, a Fine of five ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings for every ſuch firſt Offence,</hi> &amp;c. This impoſing the Fine muſt be in the ſame Record of Conviction, and not in any other Record by it ſelf, and it is not ſafe nor juſtifia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:60812:37"/>to make a Warrant to Levy any Fine, but what is contained in the Record of Conviction.</p>
               <p n="17">17. <hi>Which Record and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction ſhall be Certified by the ſaid Iuſtice at the next Quarter Seſſions,</hi> &amp;c. The next Quarter Seſſions is intended next after the Conviction, not next after the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence committed; for perhaps the Quarter Seſſions next after the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence committed, may be paſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Offenders be Convicted. <q>Next Quarter Seſſions, <hi>i. e.</hi> for the place where the Offence was committed, and the Conviction made, if by a Juſtice of the Peace for the County at large, then to the next Quarter Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons held for ſuch County, if in a Corporation, or other Liberty, by the chief Magiſtrate or Juſtice of ſuch place, then to the next Quarter Seſſions for ſuch place, if the Conviction be made by a Juſtice of the Peace of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60812:38"/>for an Offence committed in a Liberty or Corporation where the County Juſtices have a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>current Authority, then the ſame muſt be certified to the next Quarter Seſſions of the County.</q> Note by the Statute of 2 <hi>H.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. The Quarter Seſſions are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be holden in all the Counties of <hi>England</hi> four times in the year, that is to ſay, the firſt week after the Feaſt of St. <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael,</hi> and the firſt week after the <hi>Epiphany,</hi> and in the firſt week after the cloſe or end of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> and in the firſt week after the Feaſt of Tranſlation of St. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> the Martyr, which as I take it, always falls upon the <hi>7th</hi> day of <hi>July.</hi> Theſe are the four Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Seſſions: But the ſame Statute directing that the Seſſions ſhould be held oftner, if need were; the Seſſions holden at other times are called General Seſſions, but not Quarter Seſſions, by the Statute
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:60812:38"/>of 14 of <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 4. The Juſtices of <hi>Middleſex</hi> are bound to hold Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Seſſions but twice in the year, but they may (as they do) hold Quarter Seſſions at the four times of the year aboveſaid, and each of theſe Seſſions is a Quarter Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Seſſions holden at other times are General Seſſions. Now every Quarter Seſſions is a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Seſſions, yet every General Seſſions is not a Quarter Seſſions, and not holden at the time appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Statute of 2 <hi>Hen.</hi> 5. above mentioned.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 2.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>THat of ſuch Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſo Convicted as aforeſaid ſhall at any time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain commit the like Offence,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Obſ.</note> &amp;c. By this Clauſe theſe two Points are to be obſerved, (1.) He that is to be Convicted, and to incur the Penalty of 10 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> muſt
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:60812:39"/>be Guilty of ſuch Offence after the time he was Convicted of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Offence, and not only after the time he committed the former Offence; for if one commit two or more Offences before he be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vict, he may be afterwards Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed for each of theſe Offences, but he ſhall only pay a Fine of five ſhillings for each Offence, and not 10 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> for either one of them; for that though he Offended twice, or oftner, yet he never Offended after he was once Convicted. (2.) Where any one is Convicted for the ſecond Offence, whereby the Penalty of 10 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> is impoſed on him, the Record of ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction ought to mention and take notice of the Record of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Conviction.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Which Fine and Fines for the firſt and every other Offence ſhall be levyed by diſtreſs and ſale of the Offenders Goods and Chattels,</hi> &amp;c. But the Officer
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:60812:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>may ſeize ready Moneys of the Offender if he can find it in his Houſe, but he may not take it from the Perſon of the Offender, and by the word <hi>Chattels,</hi> muſt be underſtood Perſonal Chattels, which may be diſtrained, or levied as well as ſold, and therefore a Leaſe for years, or other real Chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, cannot be ſold by the Officer for levying any Penalty impoſed by virtue of this Act. <q>
                     <hi>Goods and Chattels,</hi> this reaches to the Utenſils, Tools, and Inſtruments of Trade, as well as any other Goods and Chattels; for the rule of the common Law (that exempts ſuch, (where there's ſufficient beſides) from diſtreſs,) extends not where diſtreſs is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as an Execution by any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Statute, as for Poors Rates, Hearth-money, and ſo the like on this Law, and governs on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in diſtreſſes for Rents, Amer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciaments, and the like.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:60812:40"/>
3. <hi>Or in Caſe of the Pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſuch Offender,</hi> &amp;c. What ſhall be ſaid in a caſe of Poverty, and how ſhall it be determined, I conceive the Juſtice is the Judge of it, and may determine it at the time of the Conviction, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon impoſe the Fine upon any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Convicted of the ſame Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; but if the Party Convicted be taken to be Reſponſible, and a Warrant is made to Levy, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards the Conſtable, or other Officer to whom the Warrant is directed, ſhall afterwards certify the Juſtice of the Poverty of the Offender, in that Caſe I take it, if it be within the three months, the Juſtice at his Diſcretion may impoſe the Fine upon any other Offender that is then Convicted of the ſame Offence; but if the three months are elapſed, then I think he cannot, though it is not clear. See the <hi>14th</hi> Paragraph of this Act.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:60812:40"/>
4. <hi>Vpon the Goods and Chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels of any other Perſon or Perſons who ſhall be then Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed in manner aforeſaid of the like Offence,</hi> &amp;c. That is, of being preſent at one and the ſame Conventicle. For if <hi>A.</hi> and <hi>B.</hi> be both preſent at a Conventicle, now it is the like Offence in both, conſidering the Offence in it ſelf. Now though <hi>A.</hi> hath been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly Convict, and ſo he is to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur the Penalty of 10 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> and <hi>B.</hi> having not been formerly, is to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur the Penalty of 5 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> only. Now here the Penalty is different, yet the Offence is the like, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in caſe of Poverty, the Fine of 10 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> for the Offence of <hi>A.</hi> may be impoſed on <hi>B.</hi> or the 5 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> for the Offence of <hi>B.</hi> may be impoſed upon <hi>A.</hi> or upon any other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed of being preſent at the ſame Conventicle; but I think the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher or Teacher in this Conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, is not within the meaning of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:60812:41"/>this Clauſe; for that though he be preſent, yet he is to be Convicted of a greater Offence, for taking upon him to Preach or Teach in the Conventicle, and not of the leſſer Offence of being preſent at it.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>At the Diſcretion of the ſaid Iuſtice,</hi> &amp;c. Note this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion is bounded in theſe points, (1.) There muſt be Poverty of an Offender in the Caſe (at leaſt in the Judgment of the Juſtice) or elſe there is no Room left for Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion. (2.) The ſum to be le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vyed on any one Offender in Caſe of the Poverty of others muſt not amount to above 10 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> upon occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of any one Meeting or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle. Theſe two Points being obſerved, the Law hath leſt it ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely to the Choice and Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Juſtice upon what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Offenders at the ſame Conventicle (except the Preacher or Teacher there) to impoſe the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:60812:41"/>Penalty he ſhall think fit, wherein he may do well to have regard to the eſtate, and forwardneſs to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend of ſuch Perſon or Perſons, upon whom he ſhall impoſe the Penalty.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>And every Conſtable, Head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough, Tythingman, Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens, and Overſeers of the Poor reſpectively are hereby Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized and required to levy the ſame accordingly, having firſt received a Warrant,</hi> &amp;c. The Warrant to levy the Penalties be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under Hand and Seal of the Juſtice Convicting, is in its Nature an Execution for the King, and therefore the Officer upon demand made to have the Doors opened, and declaring of his Warrant at the ſame time, may break open the Doors to enter, and make Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Warrant by levying of the Goods of the Offender, if up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch demand the Doors ſhall not be opened to him. <q>Though
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:60812:42"/>it hath been queſtioned by ſome, yet there's no colour to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; the objection they have made, is, that this is a particular mode of levying a penalty by way of diſtreſs preſcribed by an Act of Parliament, and the King hath no ſhare or intereſt therein, till diſtribution of the Money levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into three parts; but certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this is the King's Suit, 'tis a breach of his Law, a Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by his Officers, and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs is an Execution for him, the Record of Conviction is a Judgment, or Award for the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture of ſo much, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore diſtribution the whole is his, to be returned into the Seſſions, at leaſt 'tis an Execution for a third part for him, and as for that, the Doors may be broken open, and being ſo open, the reſt may be levied.</q> The reſt of this Paragraph is plain.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:60812:42"/>
               <head>SECT. 3.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>AND be it farther E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacted by the Authority aforeſaid, that every Perſon who ſhall take upon him to Preach or Teach in any ſuch Meeting,</hi> &amp;c. Here the words <hi>(every Perſon who ſhall take upon him)</hi> are general, ſo that an Alien or Perſon under the Age of 16, who ſhall take upon him to Preach, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is to be convicted, and forfeit 20 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> for the firſt Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, as well as a Denizen, or Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of the Realm, of the Age of 16 years, or upwards, (though every one that is to be Convicted for only being preſent at a Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, muſt be a Subject of the Realm, and of the Age of 16 or upwards, as is aboveſaid. <q>And here by this clauſe, if in ſuch Meeting ſeveral ſhall take upon them ſucceſſively to Preach or
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:60812:43"/>Teach, though at one time of Meeting, yet every ſuch Perſon comes within the penalty of this clauſe, and their Penalties to be levied, as in caſe there be but one.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>And if the ſaid Preacher or Teacher ſo Convicted be a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and his Name and Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not known, or is fled, and cannot be found,</hi> &amp;c. Theſe words muſt be taken in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctive (that is) if the Preacher be a ſtranger (who is preſumed to be not known (or if his Name be not known (for then he cannot be Convicted) or if his Habitation be not known, for then by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption the Penalty cannot be levied. In either of theſe Caſes the Penalty may be levied upon other Offenders preſent at the ſame Conventicle, and where the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute ſaith <hi>(not known)</hi> that muſt be intended not known to the Juſtice or Officers that ſuppreſs the Conventicle, and proſecute the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:60812:43"/>Offenders, for there is no Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on but the Preacher, and his Name and Habitation is or may be known to the Conventiclers themſelves; but if not known to the Officers, he is not known according to the intent of this Law.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Or is fled and cannot be found,</hi> &amp;c. That is ſo fled, that he cannot be found by the Officers that proſecute him for the Offence, though perhaps he is not ſo fled, but may eaſily be found by his own Diſciples.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Or in the Iudgment of the Iuſtice, Iuſtices or chief Iuſtice or Magiſtrate before whom he ſhall be Convicted, ſhall be thought unable to pay the ſame,</hi> &amp;c. This Clauſe ſuppoſeth the Teacher or Preachers Name to be known, otherwiſe he cannot be Convicted at all. I ſay the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher or Teacher cannot be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed, if his Name be not known, but by the former Clauſe, if his
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:60812:44"/>Name be not known, the Penalty of 20 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> may be impoſed upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers preſent at the ſame Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, where the Preacher or Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher's Name is known. The Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Juſtice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the Preacher's inability to pay, ought to appear upon Record under his Hand and Seal.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>The ſaid Iuſtice, Iuſtices, or chief Magiſtrate reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are hereby Impowered, and required to levy the ſame by Warrant as aforeſaid, upon the Goods and Chattels of any ſuch Perſon who ſhall be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at the ſame Conventicle, any thing in this or any other Act,</hi> &amp;c. By this Clauſe it ſeems to me that the Penalty in this Caſe may be impoſed upon any Perſon preſent at the ſame Conventicle, though ſuch Perſon upon whom it is impoſed, be not Convicted for being preſent at the Conventicle, nor can be Convicted for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:60812:44"/>preſent as an Alien or Subject under 16 years of Age: And the different penning of this and the precedent Paragraph, ſeems to make it clear; for in the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Paragraph the words are, that the Penalty there mentioned, in caſe of Poverty of ſuch Offender, (12) He is Convicted for being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at a Conventicle,) ſhall be le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vyed on the Goods and Chattels of any other Perſon or Perſons who ſhall be then Convicted in manner aforeſaid of the like Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence at the ſame Conventicle; ſo the Penalty there can be laid upon none but ſuch as by this Law are, and ought to be Convicted for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſent at the ſame Conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle; but an Alien or Subject un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der 16 years, cannot be Convicted for that Offence. But here the words of this Paragraph ſay, that the Penalty of 20 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> here men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, may be levyed upon any ſuch Perſons who ſhall be preſent
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:60812:45"/>at the ſame Conventicle, whether Convicted or not, and an Alien may be preſent at a Conventicle, though he cannot be Convicted, whereby to Forfeit 5 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> as a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject may; but the Penalty impoſed on the Preacher, ſo far as 10 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> may be levied upon him, and the <hi>non obſtante</hi> in this Paragraph doth ſeem to confirm this Conſtruction.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>And the money ſo levyed to be diſpoſed of in manner afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid,</hi> &amp;c. That is as above directed by the next precedent Paragraph, <hi>(viz.) <hi>One third to the King, one other third to the Poor of the Pariſh where the Offence was committed, and the other third to the Informer, and ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as the Iuſtice ſhall appoint.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>And if ſuch Offender ſo Convicted as aforeſaid ſhall at any time again commit the like Offence,</hi> &amp;c. The commitment of the ſaid Offence muſt be after the Conviction for the firſt. See above, § 2. Obſ. 1.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:60812:45"/>
7. <hi>ſhall for every ſuch Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence incurr the Penalty of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty pounds to be levied and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as aforeſaid.</hi> This Penalty of 40 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> may be levied upon the Preacher as the 20 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> penalty a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove; and in caſe of Inability of the Preacher, upon the Goods of others preſent at the ſame Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle, in like manner as the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty of 20 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> might.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 4.</head>
               <p>Obſ. 1. <hi>AND be it farther Enacted by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority aforeſaid, that every Perſon who ſhall wittingly and willingly ſuffer any ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle,</hi> &amp;c. Theſe words con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude Aliens as well as Denizens, and Peers as well as Commoners.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>To be held in his or her houſe,</hi> &amp;c. That is, in the Houſe or Out houſe in his or her Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereby he or ſhe might have
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:60812:46"/>hindered the Conventicle from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing held there, for in this Caſe the bare poſſeſſion of the Houſe (though without any Title) makes it to be his or her Houſe within the intent of this Law; as for Inſtance, if a man enter upon me, and put me out of Poſſeſſion of my Houſe by wrong, and keeps me out of Poſſeſſion, and in that time ſuffers a Conventicle to be holden in the ſame Houſe; now he that hath ſold the Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my Houſe, is to be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for ſuffering a Conventicle in his Houſe, though in truth the Title of the Houſe be mine.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Or in Caſe of the Poverty,</hi> &amp;c. This is in the Judgment of the Juſtice of Peace Convicting as above, in caſe of the Preacher, but the Penalty in this Caſe of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty is only to be levied upon ſuch as ſhall be Convicted for being preſent at the ſame Conventicle, and not upon Aliens, who are not
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:60812:46"/>to be Convicted for being preſent at the Conventicle. The penning of this Clauſe, and the like Clauſe in the ſecond Paragraph, do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly agree, but are both different from the Clauſe in the third Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph, where the Penalty of the Preacher, in caſe of his Poverty or inability, is to be levied on any Perſon preſent at the ſame Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle, though not Convicted.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 5.</head>
               <p n="1">1. This is clear, yet it may be doubted whether more than ten pounds may not be impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon one Perſon for the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty of the Preacher, where his Name or Habitation is not known, for that Penalty is not impoſed in regard of the Poverty, or inabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Preacher; but becauſe he is not known, ſo as the Juſtice might judge whether he were able to pay the Penalty or not. The
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:60812:47"/>Husband and Wife co-habiting, are both preſent at a Conventicle, and Convicted, whereby the penalty of 5. <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> impoſed upon the Wife, is to be levied on the Husband's Goods; yet the Husband may be charged with 10 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> beſides, for, and in regard of the Poverty of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for the Wifes Penalty of 5 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> is not laid upon the Husband in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of her Poverty, but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the Relation between them. Where there is a Penalty of twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Pounds or more to be impoſed in reſpect, the Juſtice may aſſeſs what ſum he thinks fit upon each party lyable, ſo that no one be charged with more than 10 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> in regard of Poverty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:60812:47"/>
               <head>ACT.</head>
               <head type="sub">SECT. 6.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>PRovided alſo, and be it farther Enacted, That in all Caſes of this Act, where the Penalty, or Summ charged upon any Offender, exceeds the Summ of</hi> 10 <abbr>s.</abbr> This Paragraph gives an Appeal to the Offender in certain Caſes, whereupon theſe things are to be taken notice of, (1.) The Perſon that may Appeal muſt be an Offender charged with above the ſumm or Penalty of 10 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> for if he be charged with the ſumm or Penalty of 10 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> only, or under, he is concluded by the Conviction, and cannot appear. A Conſtable Convicted upon the <hi>11th</hi> Paragraph of this Act may Appeal. (2.) The time when he may Appeal, and that muſt be within one week after the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:60812:48"/>Penalty above 10. <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> be levied upon his Goods, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or elſe after the voluntary payment of ſuch Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty either to the Officer or Juſtice Convicting, ſo that before the whole Penalty charged upon the Offender, be either levied or paid, the Offender cannot Appeal, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can he Appeal at all, if a week be elapſed after the Penalty levied or paid, and no Appeal with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in that time; but in ſuch Caſe the Offender is for ever concluded by the Conviction before the Juſtice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (3.) The manner of Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling muſt be in writing from the Perſon or Perſons Convicting <hi>(i. e.)</hi> the Juſtice or Juſtices of the Peace. But ſuch writing need not be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by the Party Appealing. (4.) The Judges to whoſe Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Appeal lyeth, are the Juſtices of Peace in their next Quarter Seſſions (that is) next af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Appeal, and not next after the levying or payment of the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:60812:48"/>money, and it muſt be the Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Seſſions for the ſame County, Liberty, or Place where the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence was committed, and the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender Convicted, and not any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <q>If it were in a Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the chief Magiſtrate, and Juſtices of the Corporation, the Certificate and return of monies levied, and the Appeal muſt be to the Seſſions for ſuch place, and not to the Quarter Seſſions for the County at large, and ſo was it ruled in the caſe of the Town of <hi>Southmolton</hi> in <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>von,</hi> to the Mayor of which place the Court of <hi>Kings-Bench, Mic.</hi> 35. <hi>Car.</hi> 2. granted a <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damus</hi> for the receiving an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal from a Conviction of a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle held in that Town, made by the chief Magiſtrate of that Corporation.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>To whom the Iuſtice or Iuſtices,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that firſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed ſuch Offender, ſhall return
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:60812:49"/>the money levied upon the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealant,</hi> &amp;c. Though the words are only the Money levied upon the Appealant; yet the Money paid by the Appealant is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned by the intent of the Law; and here is a neceſſary Caution to be obſerved by the Juſtice Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victing, that where any Penalty of above 10 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> is levied upon, or paid by one Offender, he do not proceed to make diſtribution of the Penalty ſo levied or paid, till one full week be paſt after the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vying, or payment of it, for the Offender hath that time to Appeal in, and if he doth Appeal within that time, the Juſtice is to return the whole Monies to the Seſſions; and if the Offender upon his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal be acquitted by the Seſſions, he is to be reſtored to all his Money. The Juſtice upon his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal is to certify the Record of the Conviction, and the Evidence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the Conviction paſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:60812:49"/>his Hand and Seal, and alſo the Appeal made before him in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that the Seſſions may the better be enabled to proceed, as the merits of the Cauſe ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Whereupon ſuch Offender may plead, and make defence, and have his Tryal by a Iury thereupon,</hi> &amp;c. The Offender may plead that he is not Guilty of the Offence contained in the firſt Conviction, which in this Caſe ſtands inſtead of an Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and thereupon Iſſue being joined for the King, the Appellant may give in Evidence, that it was not a Conventicle where he was preſent, but a lawfull Aſſembly, or that he was elſewhere, and not preſent at ſuch Conventicle as the Conviction ſuppoſeth, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matter that is legal Evidence for his Acquittal; and on the other ſide the Proſecutor for the King may produce, and give in Evidence
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:60812:50"/>any new matter for the proving of the Appellant guilty of the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence contained in the Conviction from which he hath ſo Appealed. And I take it, that though the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute hath indulged the Offender to plead to the Fact, and to have a Tryal by a Jury, yet if the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellant thinks fit, he may by a Demurrer inſiſt upon matter in Law at the Seſſions, for that the Conviction is inſufficient in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance (for want of Form is no exception by the <hi>13th</hi> Clauſe of this Act) as that it doth not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that any Conventicle was hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, or that it appeareth by the Record of the Conviction, that it was a lawfull Aſſembly, and not a Conventicle, or that it doth not appear that the Appealant was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at any ſuch Conventicle. In thoſe or the like Caſes, if the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellant doth demurr to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, and the Proſecutor for the King joins in demurrer, the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:60812:50"/>Court of Seſſions ought to give Judgment either for, or againſt the Appealant, as the matter in Law doth appear before them: But now let us ſee what other matters of Fact, beſides not Guilty, the Appellant may plead at the Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and firſt I conceive he may plead the Kings Pardon after the Offence committed, and before the Conviction; for after the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, the Pardon comes too late, (ſave only for the King's third part) and if ſuch pardon under the great Seal be ſhewed in Court, as it muſt be, if it be pleaded, the Court (if the Pardon appears to be ſufficient in Law) ought to diſcharge the Appealant of the Conviction, and the Penalties im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by ſuch Conviction; the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealant may likewiſe plead Auter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foits Convict, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that he was formerly Convicted of the ſame Offence, and hath paid the Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or that the ſame have been
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:60812:51"/>levied upon his Goods, and ſo ought not to be twice charged for the ſame Offence; and this is a good Plea to diſcharge him, but if the Penalties upon the other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction be not paid, or levied, then ſuch Plea of Auterfoits Convict ought not to be allowed; for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the former Conviction might be paſt by ſome contrivance of the Offender or his Agents, that the Penalties ſhould not be levied, and ſo by a mean the Offender might eſcape unpuniſhed, if the Plea of Auterfoits Convict ſhould be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed without the Penalties being levied or paid. On the other hand, it can be no miſchief to the Appellant, for though he ſtands twice Convicted for the ſame Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, yet the firſt payment of the Penalties diſchargeth him of both Convictions; for if the Penalties ſhould be again levied upon him, he hath liberty in a week after to Appeal, and upon ſhewing his
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:60812:51"/>Caſe by Plea at the Seſſions ought to be relieved, and reſtored to his Money ſo levied the ſecond time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And in Caſe ſuch Appellant ſhall not proſecute with effect,</hi> &amp;c. If at the next Quarter Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the Appealant ſhall not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, and plead matter of Fact or Demurr in Law to the Record of the firſt Conviction, this will be a Non-proſecution whereby treble Coſts are to be given againſt him, ſo that if he do not appear at the day given him, from time to time, till the Appeal be determined; but if he appears, and upon motion, the Court of Seſſion, for ſome Cauſe ſeeming reaſonable to them, do grant farther time to the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealant for drawing of his Plea, or if after Plea pleaded, they grant him farther time than ordinary for Tryal, in ſuch caſe this is no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault in the Appealant, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no Coſts to be awarded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him; ſo if the Court do take
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:60812:52"/>time to conſider of the matter in Law, this is not a Failer of Proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Appealant whereby to ſubject him to the payment of any Coſts, and in all caſes of Non-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, there muſt be a Record of it made by the Seſſions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Or if upon ſuch Tryal he ſhall not be Acquitted,</hi> &amp;c. It is not ſaid, if upon Tryal the firſt Conviction ſhall be affirmed, or found true; but, if the Appealant ſhall not be acquitted; ſuppoſe the Appealant be Convicted of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſent at a Conventicle, and 5 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> Penalty impoſed upon him, and in regard of the Poverty of the Teacher, 10 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> more is impoſed upon him, which being levied, he Appeals, and pleads that the Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher was able to pay himſelf, and therefore the Appealant ought not to have been charged with the 10 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> In this Caſe I conceive ſuch Plea is inſufficient, and though it were found ſo by verdict at the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:60812:52"/>Seſſions, yet the Appealant is not acquitted of the Offence (which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>) of being preſent at the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle, nor is the Teacher found Innocent, and therefore the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealant cannot be relieved, but ought to pay treble Coſts for his unjuſt Appeal; but what if upon the Appeal the Appealant doth not make it appear, and it is ſo found by Verdict, that though the Appealant was preſent at the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle, and thereby forfeited 5 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t the Perſon, in regard of whoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>overty the ſumm of 10 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> or any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſſer ſumm was impoſed upon the appealant, was not at all preſent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſame Conventicle. Now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Appealant is not totally acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for the Conviction of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſent at the Conventicle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ands in force; yet in this Caſe I conceive he is to be diſcharged of the other Penalty impoſed upon him, and to be excuſed from pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of any Coſts, and the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:60812:53"/>between this Caſe and the next precedent is this. In the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Caſe the Perſon in regard of whoſe Poverty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was either a Teacher, or preſent at the Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, whereby the Juſtice Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victing had a Juriſdiction to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Penalty either upon the Party himſelf, or upon ſome other; but in this caſe the Juſtice hath no Authority at all to impoſe a Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty either upon one that was not preſent at the Conventicle, or in regard of the Poverty of one that was not preſent at the Conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, which diverſity is apparent; what if the Penalty in regard of the Poverty of. another impoſed upon the Appealant, hath been im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon the Party himſelf, or upon any other, and hath been actually levied or paid? In this Caſe I think the Appealant is to be relieved againſt that Penalty, and though he be not totally ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted, yet he ought not to be charged with Coſts.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:60812:53"/>
                  <hi>Or Iudgment paſs not for him upon his ſaid Appeal,</hi> &amp;c. This Clauſe ſeems to confirm the Opinion above, that the Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant may demurr in Law to the Conviction, and pray the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Court of Seſſions up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, without Pleading to Iſſue, or having a Tryal by a Jury, as the Act ſaith. Note, that where the words are <hi>(Iudgment paſs not for him upon his ſaid Appeal)</hi> it is to be underſtood that Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment paſs not for him upon the determination of the Appeal at the end of the Suit; for whilſt the Appeal depends undetermined, it cannot be known whether Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall paſs for him or not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſaid Iuſtices at the Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſhall give treble Coſts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch Offender for his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Appeal,</hi> &amp;c. That is, the Juſtices at the Seſſion ſhall give Judgment that the Offender pay treble Coſts, for that is the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:60812:54"/>of the words, <hi>(give treble Coſts)</hi> but who ſhall have this treble Coſts? I conceive the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutor of the Conviction that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutes at the Seſſions, whoſe Name ought to appear in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of the Seſſions. But what if the Offender Appeals to the Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the Juſtice Convicting Certifies the Record of Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Evidence and the Appeal; but the Appealant doth not appear at the Seſſions at all, nor doth any thing in Proſecution of his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal; how ſhall the Proſecutors Name appear in ſuch Caſe? To this I anſwer; that in this Caſe no Coſts are to be given, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Appealant's Non-proſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be Recorded, whereby he Forfeits his Recognizance given to proſecute his Appeal with effect; but if the Appealant one appears and pleads, or demurrs, as he muſt, then the Proſecutor's Name will appear. And if afterwards the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:60812:54"/>Appeal is not Proſecuted but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continued. Then treble Coſts are to be awarded to the Proſecutor, as well as where the Offender up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Tryal is not acquitted, or Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment paſs not for him upon the determination of the Appeal.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And no other Court whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,</hi> &amp;c. By this Clauſe the Juſtice of Peace Convicting where no Appeal lieth, and the Juſtices of the Seſſion, where an Appeal is given, are made the final Judges of the Offences of being preſent at a Conventicle. And of any Perſon's taking upon him to Preach or Teach in a Conventicle, or wilfull ſuffering a Conventicle to be held in his or her dwelling Houſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And of a Conſtable's Omiſſion of the performance of his Duty in Execution of this Act, and this excluſive to the great Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi>-Hall, and all other Courts whatſoever; yet if a <hi>Certiorari,</hi> or Writ of Errour iſſue
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:60812:55"/>out of any of the great Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Hall, and be delivered either to the Juſtices Convicting, or to the Seſſions, they ought not to proceed till the Court, out of which ſuch a Writ iſſued, be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of the matter, and ſhall think fit to ſuperſede their own; for though the Juſtices of Peace, and the Seſſions, be made the final Judges of the Offences aforeſaid, yet they are not Judges of the Proceſs of the ſuperiour Courts, but only the ſuperiour Court it ſelf, out of which the Proceſs iſſued.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:60812:55"/>
               <head>SECT. 7.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>UPon the delivery of ſuch Appeal as aforeſaid,</hi> &amp;c. The time for delivery of the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal muſt be within one week next after the Penalty levied or paid, and at the time of the delivery of the Appeal in writing the Appeal is made. Now the Act appoints that a Recognizance be entred into for the proſecuting of the Appeal at the ſame time, that is, at the ſame inſtant of time the Appeal is delivered. And the Recognizance muſt have theſe Circumſtances, it muſt be entred into by the Party himſelf Appealing, and (in ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) not by any other, (though ſufficient) ſecurity for him, it muſt be acknowledged before, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the ſame Juſtice that made the Record of the Conviction; but if the Conviction be by two or more Juſtices the Appeal
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:60812:56"/>delivered to, and the Recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance acknowledged before any one of them is ſufficient. But if both, or all of the Juſtices Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victing are together, the Recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance muſt be acknowledged be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them all, though the Statute hath not appointed any ſum to be contained in the Recognizance; yet it ought to be in a reaſonable ſum, which is commonly, and uſually double the ſum in Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, which in this Caſe is double the Penalty impoſed on the Offender that Appeals. There may be ſome doubt how the Appeal is to be made, or the Recognizance entred, when the ſingle Juſtice Convicting ſhall happen to die, or be out of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction before the time of Appeal; but that being a matter rarely happening, I ſhall not ſpend time about it at preſent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:60812:56"/>
               <head>SECT. 8.</head>
               <p>THat is at the time of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Appeal, and the Appeal cannot be ſaid to be made till it be delivered, and the Recognizance entred.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 9.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>AFter refuſal or denial, to enter, break open, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into any houſe, or other place where they ſhall be informed, any ſuch Conventicle as aforeſaid is or ſhall be held, as well within Liberties as without, and take into their Cuſtodies the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons there unlawfully Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, to the intent,</hi> &amp;c. In all Caſes where the outward door of a Houſe may be broken, the Law (as this Act) doth require, That firſt, A Demand be made to have the Door opened, for Force is not
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:60812:57"/>to be uſed where the Law may be Executed in a peaceable and quiet manner. Now a refuſal or denial to enter, is not only intended of an Actual or expreſs denial, or refuſal to open the doors, but alſo of a refuſal or denial in Law, as where the Officers require the Doors to be opened, and the Conventiclers make no anſwer whether they will or will not open the Doors; or if they anſwer that they will open the Doors, but notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding they do not open the doors, this is a refuſal and denial in Law, as ſtrong as if they had expreſly refuſed or denied to open the doors; and thereupon the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers may break open the doors, and ſeize the Offenders (of mean Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticlers) and ſecure them in Cuſtody untill the Officers can conveniently bring them before a Juſtice of Peace to be Convicted, and then the Offenders are to be diſcharged out of Cuſtody. But
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:60812:57"/>what if any Offender in ſuch Caſe, being brought before a Juſtice of Peace to be Convicted, ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to diſcover his Name and Place of Habitation, whereby the Juſtice cannot proceed to a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction of him. In ſuch Caſe the Juſtice may commit him to the common Gaol for his Contempt, and by the <hi>Mittimus</hi> ſhewing the Cauſe of ſuch Commitment, the Offender will be held untill he doth diſcover his Name and Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation (for it is impoſſible he can be Bailed) for though an Offender may be committed without a Name, yet his Name muſt be known before he can be Bailed, and then the Juſtice may proceed to Convict him of the Offence, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or Preaching at the Conventicle, as the Caſe falls out, though it be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the end of three months, for that the firſt was proſecuted within the three months. Now it is to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered what is to be done, ſuppoſing
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:60812:58"/>there be a Conventicle held, and the doors are open, or upon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand made by the Officers, the doors are immediately opened, and they are permitted to enter freely; whether then the Officers may take any of the Offenders into Cuſtody or not? And I take it, that if the Conventiclers do make known their Names and places of Habitation, and do depart peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly when commanded by the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, they may not be taken into Cuſtody, becauſe in ſuch Caſe they may be Convicted without being taken into Cuſtody: But if the Offenders do refuſe to make known their Names, then ſuch of them as do ſo refuſe, may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken into Cuſtody, and if at Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Officers, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticlers refuſe to depart, or do not depart and diſperſe themſelves peaceably, they may be taken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Cuſtody likewiſe, and this ſeems clear by the latter part of this Paragraph.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:60812:58"/>
                  <hi>And that the Lieutenant or Deputy-Lieutenants,</hi> &amp;c. Here the Military Power as well as the Civil Power, is to be aſſiſting for the diſſolving, diſſipating, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting of Conventicles; but the Lieutenants or Deputy-Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are not to intermed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, before they have firſt received a Certificate under the Hand and Seal of a Juſtice of Peace or chief Magiſtrate of his particular infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation or knowledge of any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull Meeting or Conventicle held or to be held, and that he with ſuch Aſſiſtance is not able to ſuppreſs and diſſolve the ſame. This Certificate may be made ſometime before the Conventicle held as well as at the time; and though it cannot be ſo well known before hand, whether the Juſtice or chief Magiſtrate with ſuch Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be able to ſuppreſs the Conventicle or not; yet if the Juſtice hath reaſon, or any proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:60812:59"/>ground to believe that he ſhall not be able to ſuppreſs the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle, whereof he hath notice, he may make his Certificate, that the Military Power may be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; for if a Certificate ſhould not be made till the very time of the Conventicle held, it would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps be too late for the ſuppreſſing of them, and the words of the Act are, <hi>To prevent ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull Meetings as well as to diſſolve and diſperſe them. And note, that if there be ſuch a Conventicle as cannot be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by the Iuſtice himſelf with ſuch Aſſiſtance as he can get, but there is need of Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Power, or ſome other grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter power to be raiſed by the Sheriff or other Officer, in ſuch caſe the Conventiclers, or ſo many of them as the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers ſuppreſſing of them ſhall think fit, Peers of the Realm only excepted, may be taken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:60812:59"/>Cuſtody, and kept in Cuſtody for ſuch convenient time, till they ſhall be Convicted by the Iuſtice or chief Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate. But ſuppoſe the Iuſtice that would ſuppreſs the Conventicle, be himſelf a Deputy-Lieutenant, and he as a Iuſtice is not able to ſuppreſs the Conventicle, I conceive in ſuch</hi> 
                  <q>Caſe he may make uſe of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Power, and get ſuch Troops or Companies of Horſe and Foot, as he ſhall think meet, and can get in readineſs with the ſooneſt; by this Law any Juſtice of the Peace, Conſtable, or other Officer going in Execution of this Act to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs and diſperſe ſuch unlawfull Aſſembly, they may call or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand any Perſon whatſoever in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Aid or Aſſiſtance, and in Caſe of refuſal they are puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, as by the <hi>11th</hi> Section, ſee hereafter; And did not this Law expreſly enable them to do it, they might do it by the general Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of their Offices in this Caſe, as they may for the ſuppreſſing of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frays, Riots, Routs, and other un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull Aſſemblies.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:60812:60"/>
                  <hi>And take into their cuſtody ſuch perſons ſo aſſembled as they ſhall think fit.</hi> 
                  <q>Some are of opinion, and it hath been ſo reſolved, that by force of theſe words they may impriſon any of them for any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient time in order to examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not only of their own names and places of Abode, but of the Teacher or the like; and that the Military Power they may uſe in taking and detaining of ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons till examined of ſuch things as may be needfull for the making a Conviction of ſuch Meeting or Aſſembly, and this they ground upon the words <hi>as they ſhall think fit: <hi>Sed quaere,</hi>
                     </hi> for the Lord <hi>Saun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> his opinion afore: <hi>Pag.</hi> 76. ſeems more conſonant to the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of this Clauſe, <hi>viz.</hi> that their Commitment is to be only till make known their own names and places of Abode, that <hi>they</hi> may be proceeded againſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Provided alwaies that no dwelling Houſe of any Peer</hi>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:60812:60"/>
                  <hi>of this Realm,</hi> &amp;c. <q>This ſeems not to extend to the dwelling Houſe of any Dutcheſs, Counteſs, Baroneſs, or other Noblewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, but they may be ſearched by virtue of this Act, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this Clauſe, as by the reading of it appears plain, it being ſaid to be ſuch Houſe where he or his Wife ſhall be Reſident; this muſt be meant actually Reſident, and therefore extends not to any Houſe which a Peer hath leaſed to another, nor to any Manſion Houſe unin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited, or wherein he hath on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Servants, and doth not Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally reſide in; for ſuppoſe a Peer have ſeveral Houſes, to which he repairs at ſeveral Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the year, and hath Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants in all, and a Meeting prohibited by this Law doth hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to be held in ſuch of his ſaid Houſes, where at that time he nor his Wife is reſident, ſuch
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:60812:61"/>Houſe may be ſearched by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of this Act, and broken open too for the diſperſing ſuch Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, for the words are, <hi>ſhall he reſident</hi> at ſuch time: If a Conventicle be held in any Barn, Stable, or other like of a Peer's, not being parcel of his dwelling Houſe, ſuch place may be ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, though the ſame be in the poſſeſſion of a Peer: And not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this Clauſe, a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction may be made of ſuch a Meeting that has been held in the dwelling Houſe of a Peer, though he be reſident in it, and ſuch Peer incurrs the Penalty of this Act as Owner of the Houſe, permitting the ſame. See above on the <hi>4th</hi> Section.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Except in the preſence of,</hi> &amp;c. Such dwelling Houſe feems not ſearchable by any Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration Juſtice, he not being named in this exception, but a Lieutenant, or Deputy Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:60812:61"/>of ſuch County, may ſearch ſuch a Houſe upon the Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Juſtice of the Peace, though he be no Juſtice him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, nor of the ſame Riding.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 11.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>BE it farther Enacted, that if any Conſtable,</hi> &amp;c. <q>This Clauſe extends to his not execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting any Warrant for levying the Penalties of this Act by diſtreſs, as well as to his not informing ſome Juſtice of a Conventicle whereof he knows; ſo if he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form not ſome Juſtice thereof (when he conveniently may) till the Meeting be over, and ſo they could not be ſuppreſſed, nor the Perſons ſo well known, in order to the making of a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction: If a Conſtable, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> keep or ſuffer a Conventicle in his Houſe, he forfeits the Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of 20 <abbr>
                        <hi>l.</hi>
                     </abbr> for ſo doing, and 5 <abbr>
                        <hi>l.</hi>
                     </abbr>
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:60812:62"/>for not informing a Juſtice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the like if he be preſent at any Meeting, and not in order to detect it; he may be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for being ſo preſent, and ſued for the 5 <abbr>
                        <hi>l.</hi>
                     </abbr> alſo, for they are ſeveral Offences: <hi>Credibly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed,</hi> &amp;c. ſuch Information as another gives him of his ſight of ſundry Perſons going to an Houſe ſuſpected, or generally uſed for ſuch purpoſes at ſuch times as uſual, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is ſufficient information to oblige the Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to acquaint the Juſtice, for a leſs information here will ſerve him than a Juſtice of the Peace for to make a Conviction, the Juſtice is to have it upon Oath, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Conſtable, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is not Judge of the truth of the Fact, he is only a Miniſterial Officer or Servant in this Caſe. A Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, or Tything Man or the like, that gives notice of his Warrant, or of a Juſtices co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:60812:62"/>to ſuppreſs ſuch Meeting is undoubtedly Guilty of this Offence, and beſides liable to be Indicted at common Law for any ſuch misfeazance or neglect, it being contrary to his Oath and Office, by the Authority of this Act 'tis become the Duty of his Office to which he is ſworn, any breach whereof is Indictable at common Law, and puniſhable by Fine and Impriſonment, and this may be too often neceſſary, in the laſt Caſe, I mean eſpecially, the 5 <abbr>
                        <hi>l.</hi>
                     </abbr> penalty ſeeming too ſmall for an Offence of ſuch a Nature; but note, then he cannot or ought not to be puniſhed both ways, for 'tis but one Offence, though when proſecuted as on this Law the Fine is certain, as at common Law 'tis undetermined. If a Conſtable uſes not all Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full means to prevent, ſuppreſs, and get Convicted ſuch Meetings, as if he breaks not open a door
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:60812:63"/>after requeſt to have it opened in execution of a Warrant to levy the penalty by virtue of this Act, he is an Offender by this Clauſe.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Every Perſon whatſoever refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing or neglecting to give his Aid (being called thereto in execution of this Act) forfeits 5 <abbr>
                        <hi>l.</hi>
                     </abbr> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, if ſuch whom the Juſtice or Conſtable ſhall call in, do by private notices or otherwiſe, forewarn thoſe Aſſembled to withdraw, for to prevent their being known, and by conſequence their being Convicted.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>If any Iuſtice of the Peace, or chief Magiſtrate, ſhall wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly or wilfully omit the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of his Duty in the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of this Act, he ſhall forfeit</hi> 100 <hi>
                        <abbr>l.</abbr> &amp;c.</hi> This Clauſe is general, omit the performance of his Duty which is by all lawfull ways to get Information and notice of all ſuch Meetings open or clan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtine, that are held within his
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:60812:63"/>Limit, Precinct, or Juriſdiction, every thing which is prohibited by the Law, a Juſtice is bound as a good Officer, not only to puniſh it when diſcovered, but by all convenient means to inform himſelf, if ſuch Offences are committed, and ſuch Offences the more ſecret, the more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous; and therefore every Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers Duty is to detect them, to be ready to receive Informations, to grant Warrants to Conſtables, to go in Perſon and endeavour to diſperſe them when met, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent their Meeting, to impriſon thoſe that oppoſe or reſiſt them, to break open Doors, if ſhut againſt them, to ſecure ſuch Offenders till know their Names and Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of abode in order to make Convictions, and of ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions to make Records to grant Warrants on them for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes, ſuch Records to certify to the next Seſſions, and in ſhort,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:60812:64"/>to do every thing which this Act Authorizes and requires them to do, and in the beſt and moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient way that may be for the Attainment of the end of this Law, which was the ſuppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and prevention of Seditious Conventicles, a wilfull neglect of any thing this Act impowers ſuch Juſtice of the Peace to do in order to that end, is an Offence within this Clauſe, and incurrs the Penalty of 100 <abbr>
                        <hi>l.</hi>
                     </abbr>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Iuſtice of Peace or thief Magiſtrate,</hi> &amp;c. It muſt be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for, or in Relation to Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences committed within their Reſpective Juriſdictions, for this Clauſe puniſhes nothing but the omiſſion of what they were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powered, or inabled to do by the foregoing part of this Law, <hi>viz.</hi> to a Corporation Juſtice, for what happens within the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration, <hi>&amp;c. &amp; ſic reſpective,</hi> although it be here ſaid any
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:60812:64"/>Juſtice or chief Magiſtrate, yet any Juſtice of the Peace in any Liberty, City, or Corporation, is within this Clauſe as well as the chief Magiſtrate of ſuch Liberty, City, or Corporation, for ſuch Juſtices are bound by the former Clauſes to diſperſe ſuch Meetings, and make Conviction of them, and by conſequence they are here intended.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Wittingly or wilfully omit,</hi> for the ſatisfying of thoſe words, either his own knowledge or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation is ſufficient, I do not mean <hi>of the Law</hi> in the Caſe, for he is bound to take notice of this and all other Acts relating to his Office, and a pretence that he knew not he had power, or that 'twas his Duty, will be no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, but his own knowledge or information of the Fact; for if a Juſtice do not ſuppreſs a Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, nor make a Conviction thereof, he is no Offender, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:60812:65"/>he have no notice of it, but yet if a Juſtice know a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle to be held in the next Houſe, and he do not his Duty, he is puniſhable by this Clauſe, though no Informer came and gave him notice of it; If any one come to inform him of a Conventicle that hath been held, he is bound to give the Informer his Oath, and 'tis no excuſe for him that the Informer did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire him to tender an Oath, for his coming is impliedly a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, it being in order to make a Conviction, and if he refuſes or omits to give him his Oath, in order to the making a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, he is puniſhable, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Conventicle were held yea or no, for being informed there was one, he is an Offender in not taking the Information upon Oath, and ſo was it reſolved by the Court of <hi>Kings-Bench, Mic.</hi> 34 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <hi>Banco Regis,</hi> on a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:60812:65"/>in Arreſt of Judgment, in an Action between <hi>Smith qui tam,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>verſ. Langham</hi> of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thamptonſhire.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>The one moiety to the uſe of the Informer,</hi> &amp;c. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be not expreſly decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto whom the other moie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhall be given, yet the King ſhall have it, for whereſoever a forfeiture or penalty is given by any Act of Parliament upon any Offence, it is intended to be to the King, his Heirs and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours, though not particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly named, unleſs it be otherwiſe ſpecially Ordered; <hi>Informer</hi> here is meant, not he that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms the Juſtice, but he that ſues for the 100 <abbr>
                        <hi>l.</hi>
                     </abbr> and ſo informs the King's Court of ſuch an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence committed by ſuch a Juſtice, for otherwiſe the Juſtice may go unpuniſhed by agreeing with him that is Informer in the firſt ſenſe, beſides, if none but
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:60812:66"/>ſuch Informer might bring the Action, there would in all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability be a failure of proof in this Caſe, for none but thoſe who informed the Juſtice, are for the moſt part capable of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Juſtice's refuſal, or neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect to do his Duty; Although a Moiety be here given to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former, yet if none will ſue for the ſame, the whole may be ſued for at the King's Suit, for there being a Forfeiture created by the Act, and by the Law given to the King, the not ſuing by any Informer for his part, ſhall not prejudice the King, the Moiety going only to the Informer <hi>(i.e.)</hi> to him that will and doth ſue for the ſame, if none will ſue for it, the whole is the King's, and before any Information, Action or popular Suit brought, he may pardon or releaſe the whole Penalty, and it ſhall be a good Bar againſt all men; but what if an offending
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:60812:66"/>Juſtice within this Law ſhould get a Friend to file an Informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt him by conſent, to prevent and anticipate a real In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former, and ſuch Prior Suit the Offender ſhould plead to the real Informer's Action to trice him thereof? I anſwer, that ſuch Plaintiff may by virtue of 4 <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 20. aver the former Suit to be by Covin and Colluſion, and ſuch Covin he may in his repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation plead generally, and if the former Suit be found to be by Covin to evade the Act, and trice the preſent Plaintiff, the Defendant ſhall ſuffer two years Impriſonment, and ſuch aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Plaintiff may make, though on the firſt Suit there were a Verdict for the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant for want of Evidence or the like, nay, though there were a recovery againſt him.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:60812:67"/>
               <head>SECT. 12.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF any Perſon be at any time ſued for putting any of the Powers of this Act in Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> &amp;c. <q>Whether it be for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming, diſturbing, ſearching, impriſoning, or diſtraining, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By the <hi>7th</hi> and 21 <hi>Jac.</hi> all Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Peace, Conſtables, and ſeveral other Officers have this privilege if ſued for any thing done by Colour of their Office, they may plead the general Iſſue, and give ſpecial matter for their excuſe or juſtification in Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; but this Act gives the ſame advantage to all manner of Perſons doing any Act in the Execution of this Statute, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they are Officers, or no, and the end is to prevent their being prejudiced by a nicety of pleading, and that the truth of their excuſe may fairly and clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:60812:67"/>appear upon Evidence, any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former or other Perſon going in Aſſiſtance of any Officer for the executing any power given by this Law, hath the ſame privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege and benefit.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Every ſuch Defendant ſhall have his full treble coſts,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>(i.e.)</hi> 
                  <q>the Coſts given by the Jury in caſe of Trial, and the Coſts likewiſe gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by the Court, <hi>de incremento</hi> are to be trebled both, ſuch Coſts as the Defendant would have in caſe this Law were not, he is now to have treble, and in caſe the Plaintiff be non-ſuit, if without Evidence, or after Evidence he ought to have thrice ſo much Coſts as he other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſhould have in ſuch Caſe.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 13.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND be it farther Enacted by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority aforeſaid, that this Act, and all Clauſes therein contained, ſhall be conſtrued moſt largely and beneficial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the ſuppreſſing of Conventicles,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:60812:68"/>and for the Iuſtification and Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all Perſons to be imployed in the execution thereof:</hi> 
                  <q>This Clauſe ſhews the deep ſenſe our Law-makers had of the pernicious effects of ſuch unlawfull Meetings, which is em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatically expreſſed in the pream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of this Act, where the reaſon of this Clauſe, and of the whole Act is declared,</q> 
                  <hi>
                     <hi>(viz.)</hi> For providing farther and more ſpeedy remedies againſt the growing and dangerous practires of Seditious Sectaries, and other Diſloyal Perſons, who under the pretence of ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Conſciences, have or may at their Meetings contrive Inſurrections</hi> (<q>as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience hath ſhewn) and that experience hath been much more abundant of late days, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Act continues as neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry as ever, it being too well known that the Perſons ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to a greater tenderneſs of Conſcience than the reſt of the Chriſtian world, are no leſs diſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected to the Engliſh Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:60812:68"/>than they avow themſelves to be to the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and it ſeems to be a baſe reflexion on the Wiſedom and prudence of our Law-makers, that the proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Law ſhould be thought unneceſſary in the ſame age where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in 'twas made, and the reaſon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing for which it was at firſt provided, <hi>viz.</hi> the danger of Muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and Sedition, for the prevention and ſuppreſſing whereof there is no better means than the Execution of this Act, which (as this Clauſe is) ought to have the largeſt and moſt beneficial Conſtruction imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>(i. e.)</hi> ſuch an equitable Conſtruction, (although it be a Penal Law) as may beſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to the ſuppreſſion of ſuch Conventicles, though perhaps the thing be not expreſly within the letter of the Law, yet it ought to be conſtrued within the intent; as for inſtance, ſuppoſe a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain number of men ſhould meet
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:60812:69"/>and Aſſemble themſelves toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther under the colour and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of exerciſing Religion, and there ſhould be no formal Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and Teaching, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an extempore Enthuſiaſtical Prayer, yet the Prolocutor, or Speaker in ſuch Aſſembly ought to be conſtrued with the intent of the third Section of this Act, and incurr the Penalty of 20 <abbr>
                        <hi>l.</hi>
                     </abbr> being certainly within the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, though not within the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe Letter of that Clauſe; the like of the Quakers Meetings, though they cannot properly be within the third Section, when 'tis as they call it a ſilent Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, yet even ſuch Aſſembly of them ſeems to be within the firſt Section, and is a Conventicle within the meaning of this Act, for 'tis a Meeting under colour of the exerciſe of Religion, though none be exerciſed, they
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:60812:69"/>pretending that they meet out of Conſcience, and for ſuch pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and 'tis plainly within the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief,</q> 
                  <hi>
                     <hi>viz.</hi> The danger of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving Mutinies and Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections at ſuch Aſſemblies,</hi> 
                  <q>and there's as much danger of that in ſuch Congregations as any other; and by the deſign of this Clauſe ſuch Conſtruction ought to be made, as may moſt ſuppreſs the Miſchief intended to be remedied by this Act; the like equitable Conſtruction ought to be made for the encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and juſtification of the Officers of Juſtice, and others employed in the Execution of this Act, the meaning of which is, that by no ſtrained interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ought ſuch Perſons to be brought to damage for any thing done by colour of this Statute; and ſo this Clauſe requires all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to be given to ſuch Perſons by the King's Courts of
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:60812:70"/>Record of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> upon all occaſions, and particularly by the next Clauſe,</q> which is, that <hi>No Record, Warrant, or</hi> Mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timus <hi>to be made by virtue of this Act or any Proceedings there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſhall be reverſed, avoided, or any way impeached for any default in Form, <hi>(i. e.)</hi>
                  </hi> 
                  <q>No Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of Conviction, Warrant, for to diſperſe a Conventicle, or to levy the Penalty by diſtreſs, or <hi>Mittimus</hi> to Priſon, ſhall, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This extends to all Courts, as to the Seſſions, ſo to the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> or any other Court where ſuch Record, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, or otherwiſe come in queſtion upon any Action that may be brought againſt any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for any thing done in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of this Act; although the Court of <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> may by <hi>Certiorari</hi> command ſuch Records to be removed thither, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet it is a good Act of their
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:60812:70"/>legal diſcretion to deny ſuch <hi>Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiorari</hi>'s as of late years is done; it being a Writ diſcretionary, and not <hi>ex debito Juſtitiae</hi> ſent only to certify his Majeſty in his ſaid Court of the Procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings againſt ſuch a Man, and the Juſtices below are the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Judges of the Fact, and this Act ſeems to order the final determination of ſuch Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences to the Juſtices particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, for that this very Law gives an Appeal to the Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons where the Party hath his advantage for matter of Law as well as Fact; but it may be queſtioned what ſhall be deemed a default in Form? I confeſs that may be of ſome difficulty, but however by the virtue of this Clauſe, though it be by a Penal Law it ought to be helped by Intendments and Preſumptions as much as
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:60812:71"/>any Plea in Bar, or any other pleading in a Civil Action, but to make the beſt Judgment in this Caſe, will be to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare this Clauſe with the Statute of Demurrs, <hi>viz.</hi> the 27 <hi>Elizabeth, cap.</hi> 5. where the words are,</q> 
                  <hi>any imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, defect, or want of Form,</hi> and the words here are, <hi>by reaſon of any default in Form,</hi> 
                  <q>which are plainly all one; upon the former the rule is, whatſoever it is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which the right doth ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently appear to the Court, it is form within that Law, and ſo <hi>è converſo,</hi> whatſoever is wanting, or imperfect, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the right appears not, is not remedied as Form within that Statute; ſo here whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it is without which the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence doth ſufficiently appear to the Court that's Form within our
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:60812:71"/>Law, ſo if it appear a Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle were held againſt this Law, and the Parties meant to be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed were preſent at it, if there be but ſufficient expreſt that it may appear upon the whole Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord the Party Convicted is an Offender againſt this Law, 'twill be well enough, and there needs no more, for which ſee above un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the firſt Section, the deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Conventicle, which will direct you how ſuch a Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ought to be made, as the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident hereafter given you is;</q> 
                  <hi>And in Caſe any Perſon offending againſt this Law ſhall flie into any other County or Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> &amp;c. <q>This Clauſe makes proviſion for the puniſhment of ſuch Perſons Convicted on this Act as are Strangers inhabiting, or Fugitives flying into any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther County or Corporation, that muſt be meant ſuch Corporation where the Juſtice Convicting
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:60812:72"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="105" facs="tcp:60812:72"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="106" facs="tcp:60812:73"/>hath no Juriſdiction, ſo as the Penalty cannot be levied by his Warrant, and therefore this Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph provides that there may be a Certificate made of ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction under the Hand and Seal of ſuch Juſtice as made it, that muſt be meant a Certificate that there is ſuch Conviction made, or a tranſcript thereof under the Juſtices Hand and Seal, not the very Record of Conviction it ſelf, for that perhaps may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned into the Seſſions and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers other Perſons inhabiting where the Offence was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted may be perhaps Convicted by the ſame Record, and then 'twould be inconvenient to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmit that ſame; it may be to any Juſtice of the Peace of ſuch other County or Corporation, and if ſuch Offender be inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or fled into a Corporation where the County Juſtices have nothing to doe, there the Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:60812:73"/>may be to any Juſtice of that Corporation, as well as to the chief Magiſtrate of the ſame, notwithſtanding the wilfull Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of ſome who in Corporations would have none but the chief Magiſtrate of that Corporation as Mayor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and no other Juſtice of ſuch place impowered by this Law, whereas the whole tenour of the foregoing Sections ſhews the contrary; ſuch Juſtice is to levy the ſaid Penalties as fully as the Juſtice Convicting might, <hi>&amp;c. (i.e.)</hi> by Warrant for diſtreſs and Sale of the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders Goods and Chattels, but it may be queried what ſhall ſuch Foreign Juſtice doe with Money ſo levied? I think this ſomewhat plain that he ought to return it to the Juſtice that did Convict, and he to the Quarter Seſſions for the place where the Offence was committed, and the Foreign Juſtice muſt not return
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:60812:74"/>it to the Quarter Seſſions of his own County, and my Reaſons are, Firſt, Becauſe the Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are not to be returned thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Secondly, A third part of ſuch Penalties is to go to the Poor of the Pariſh where the Offence was committed. Thirdly, The third is to go to the Informer or Informers, or ſuch other Perſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which diſtribution the Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Seſſions cannot convenient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make; but then it may be queried what will become of the Parties Appeal, how ſhall that be made? I anſwer, if he has the benefit of any, as I think he has notwithſtanding, it muſt be to the Quarter Seſſions of the place where the Offence was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for the Statute expreſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires it ſhould be delivered to the Juſtice Convicting, he is to take Recognizance for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution thereof with effect, and this with the Conviction he is
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:60812:74"/>to return into the Seſſions; but then it may be again queried how ſuch Offender ſhall know who is the Juſtice Convicting, for to him he muſt deliver his Appeal in writing, and that within a week after the Penalty paid or levied? I anſwer, that will be known by the Warrant of the Foreign Juſtice upon which the levy is made, for his Warrant either mentions a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction by himſelf, or by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Juſtice of another County or Corporation which will inform him, but he muſt take this Note with him always, that his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal muſt be delivered in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, for he himſelf is to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Recognizance to Proſecute it, and this is to be done at the ſame time before the Juſtice Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victing, the reſt of this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph is plain enough.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:60812:75"/>
               <head>SECT. 14.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PRovided alſo that no Perſon ſhall be puniſhed for any Offence againſt this Act, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs,</hi> &amp;c. <q>
                     <hi>Proſecuted</hi> within three months, 'tis not neceſſary that the Penalties be actually le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied within three months, nor that a Conviction be made of Record, but to fulfill the ſenſe of this Clauſe, I think it ſufficient, if Information be given to ſome Juſtice of a Conventicle already held in order to the making a Conviction of it, this being within three months, is enough, for ſuch Information being in order to a Conviction, is a Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution within the meaning of this Clauſe, it is not ſaid Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed, but Proſecuted, and ſuch Information is a commencement of the Suit, this is the <hi>primum movens</hi> towards a Conviction af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:60812:75"/>the Offence committed; as in civil Actions which are limited to be brought within ſuch a time, the beginning of a Suit is the ſuing an Original, or other firſt Writ as <hi>Latitat, &amp;c.</hi> If within the time limited, is well enough, though the Suit be not effectually Proſecuted, though there be no Judgment in a long while after, ſo in Capital Criminal Cauſes, which muſt be Proſecuted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a certain time, by the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of any particular Law, if an Indictment be found within the certain time, if the firſt Act of the Suit be begun, 'tis enough, though the Party be not Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed within twice the time, ſo here the ſame rule will govern, <hi>no Perſon ſhall,</hi> this extends to an offending Juſtice or Conſtable, as well as to the Conventicles; yet if ſuch Juſtice, Conſtable, or other Officer neglects his Duty againſt the Tenour of this Act,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:60812:76"/>be Indicted, or otherwiſe ſued within three Months after ſuch neglect or refuſal to doe their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, it is a ſufficient Proſecution within the three months, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though not Convicted within that time, as I ſaid before; and that <hi>no Perſon who is puniſhed by this Statute, ſhall be puniſhed for the ſame Offence by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Law;</hi> For the ſame Offence, notwithſtanding this, a Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticler may be puniſhed for his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence from Church, becauſe ſuch Meeting and his abſence are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Offences; <hi>Shall be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed,</hi> this doth not hinder but that ſuch Offender may be Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted and puniſhed, as at the common Law for any thing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited by this Statute, which is an Offence at the common Law, I ſay he may be Proſecuted as at common Law, if he hath been actually puniſhed for the very ſame Offence by virtue of
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:60812:76"/>this Law, but if he hath been once puniſhed by this Law, if ſued as at common Law, or on another Statute he may plead his Conviction and puniſhment on this thereto, but this he cannot do till the Penalty be either le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied or paid, for till then he is not puniſhed; however, as I ſaid, any Offender within this Law may be ſued as at common Law, as a Conventicler may for a Riot, Rout, or unlawfull Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, and puniſhed for it by Fine or Impriſonment, but he ſhall not be puniſhed both ways, and that's the ſole meaning of this Paragraph, <hi>
                        <hi>viz.</hi> That ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhould not be double puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for one and the ſame Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence;</hi> but yet again if any Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, Teacher, or other Perſon ſhould at ſuch Meeting ſpeak Seditious or Treaſonable words, reſiſt the Magiſtrate coming to diſperſe them, or give opprobrious Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:60812:77"/>to the Juſtice or other Officer in the Execution of this Act, he may be Indicted and puniſhed for any ſuch Offence, and by this Act too.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 15.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PRovided alſo that every Alderman of</hi> London, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                  <q>Had this Clauſe not been added, it would be no great Queſtion but that they were included in the meaning of this Act, for they are the chief Magiſtrates and Juſtices of the Place, this Proviſo therefore ſeems added for perſpicuity and preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all ſcruple, and for to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power ſuch of the Aldermen un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Chair, as are not Juſtices of the Peace; for it will not be doubted, but the Aldermen of <hi>Exeter</hi> and <hi>Briſtol,</hi> and other ſuch like Cities and Counties as are Juſtices of the Peace, are bound by
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:60812:77"/>this Act to prevent, diſperſe, and ſuppreſs ſuch Meetings, otherwiſe the Act would be of leaſt force where 'tis moſt needfull, <hi>viz.</hi> in thoſe Populous Cities where the moſt idle People likelieſt to be ſeduced, whereas in other Counties the common People are generally employed in hard la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour either about Husbandry or other painfull Callings, and by conſequence not ſo liable to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Provided that if the Perſon Offending and Convicted be a Feme-Covert, co-habiting,</hi> &amp;c. <q>In this caſe Co-habitation as a Wife, is a ſufficient Evidence her being ſo, and the Juſtice need look no farther, for the Husband's Goods and Chattels are liable. Co-habiting <hi>(i. e.)</hi> for the moſt part, or generally, for though ſhe be in Countrey Houſe about this Town, and her Husband in
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:60812:78"/>
                     <hi>London,</hi> yet his Goods will be liable; if it had been otherwiſe, 'twould have ſaid then Co-habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, or then Perſonally reſiding, ſo if the Husband be upon any Occaſion from home, for Co-habitation here is uſed only in oppoſition to a ſeparate living by ſentence of Spiritual Court, or by agreement of themſelves, not being apart now and then, or at certain Seaſons of the year, or on an occaſional Journey, for in all ſuch Caſes the Husband is ſtill ſuppoſed to have the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand over his Wife, ſo far as to reſtrain her from breaking this Law, and in caſe ſhe offends, 'tis to be ſuppoſed by his conſent or connivance, and therefore this Law lays the Puniſhment upon his ſhoulders.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:60812:78"/>
               <head>SECT. 16.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PRovided alſo that no Peer of this Realm ſhall be Attached or Impriſoned by force of this Act,</hi> &amp;c. <q>
                     <hi>Peer</hi> here ſeems to include all ſuch as by Law are Privileged from Perſonal Arreſts in Civil Actions, Attached or Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, is in their Bodies, for their Goods may be diſtrained upon a Conviction for ſuch a Meeting as well as any Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, this is merely deſigned to privilege their Perſons from all trouble, who are <hi>Conſanguinei &amp; Comites Regis,</hi> and always intended to be buſied <hi>in ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duis negotiis regni,</hi> in the Service of his moſt Sacred Majeſty.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:60812:79"/>
               <head>SECT. 17.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PRovided alſo that this Act, nor any thing therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, ſhall extend to invali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date or avoid his Majeſties Supremacy in Eccleſiaſtical Affairs, but that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, his Heirs and Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours may from time to time, and at all times hereafter exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe and enjoy all Powers and Authority in Eccleſiaſtical Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs as fully and as amply as any of his Predeceſſors have or might have done the ſame, any thing in this Act notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</hi> 
                  <q>This Clauſe is an ample affirmance of the King's Prerogative in Eccleſiaſtical Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs notwithſtanding this Act, which I ſhall not preſume here to diſcuſs, eſpecially conſidering that it will no way be inſtructive for the better Execution of the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:60812:79"/>Powers and Proviſions of this Act, which was the only end of our great Judge in making theſe Obſervations, and is the end of their preſent publication, and therefore I ſhall here conclude with this one Remark, <hi>viz.</hi> That the time of making this Act is mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken in the Print, which may be of uſe to obſerve in caſe any Action be brought againſt any Juſtice of the Peace or other Perſon for the 100 <abbr>
                        <hi>l.</hi>
                     </abbr> Penalty for the neglect of his Duty, 'tis there ſaid to be at a Parliament continued by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation to the <hi>14th</hi> of <hi>Febr.</hi> 1669/70 from whence it is continued by Adjournment made the <hi>11th</hi> of <hi>April,</hi> 1670. to the <hi>24th</hi> day of <hi>October</hi> following, which makes a kind of diſcontinuance, for it ſays the Adjournment made the <hi>11th</hi> of <hi>April,</hi> from the <hi>14th</hi> of <hi>Feb.</hi> before, 'tis ſafeſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to omit the Adjournments and take no notice of them, but
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:60812:80"/>only at a Parliament begun at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the <hi>8th</hi> of <hi>May, An. Dom.</hi> 1661. in the <hi>13th</hi> year of, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and there continued by ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Prorogations to the <hi>14th</hi> of <hi>Febr.</hi> 1669/70 and no more.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="memorandum">
            <pb n="121" facs="tcp:60812:80"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Midd' MEmorandum,</hi> Quod de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimo die <hi>Novembris,</hi> 
               <q>anno Regni Domini noſtri Sereniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimi <hi>Caroli</hi> Secundi Deigratia <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliae, Scotiae, Franciae</hi> &amp; <hi>Hiberniae,</hi> Regis fidei defenſoris, &amp;c. triceſimo quinto venit <hi>J.S.</hi> de in Com' <hi>Midd' Yeoman,</hi> coram nobis ad tunc &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huc duobus Juſticiar' dicti Domini Regis ad pacem ſuam pro com' praed' conſervand' aſſignat' apud <hi>S.</hi> in com' praed' Et dedit nobis intelligi &amp; informari de quodam Conventiculo &amp; illicit' aſſemblation' ſub colore ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eolendi Religionem in alio modo quam ſecund' liturgiam &amp; uſum Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae Anglicanoe ante tunc tempus
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:60812:81"/>tent' contraformam ſtatut' Et ſuper inde Examinatione debitâ adtunc &amp; ibid' habitâ tam per Sacrament' praed' <hi>J.S. &amp; A.B.</hi> de, <hi>&amp;</hi> c. <hi>&amp; C.D.</hi> de, <hi>&amp;</hi> c. coram nobis in eâ parte le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitimo modo praeſtit' quam per noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam Evidentiam facti nobis Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciariis praed' manifeſte <hi>&amp;</hi> plene ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paret quod <hi>M. N.</hi> de, <hi>&amp;</hi> c. <hi>L. M.</hi> de, <hi>&amp;</hi> c. cum multis aliis, in toto ſe attingent' ad numerum vigint' perſonarum praeter familiam praed' <hi>M. N. &amp;</hi> quilibet eorum die domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicâ, <hi>viz.</hi> Primo die hujus inſtantis <hi>Novembris,</hi> ultra aetatem ſexdecim annor' <hi>&amp;</hi> ſubdit' dict' Domini Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis nunc exiſtentes praedicto primo die hujus <hi>Novembris</hi> in ſimul aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblaverunt &amp; praeſentes fuerunt, <hi>&amp;</hi> quilibet eorum praeſens fuit in domo manſionali ipſius <hi>M.N.</hi> in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochia de in Com' praed' ad Conventiculum ſub pretextu Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citationis Religionis in alio modo quam allocatur per Liturgiam aut
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:60812:81"/>uſum Eccleſiae Anglicanae, adtune <hi>&amp;</hi> ibid' tent' contra formam Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tut' ad praevenienda <hi>&amp;</hi> ſuppri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menda ſeditioſa Conventicula nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per edit' &amp; proviſ. Ac etiam quod praed' <hi>M. N.</hi> tempore <hi>&amp;</hi> loc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ultime ſupradictis ſcienter <hi>&amp;</hi> vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarie permiſit Conventiculum praed' fore tenend' in domo manſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nali ſua praed' etiam contra for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam Statut' praed', quodque praed' <hi>O. P.</hi> tempore <hi>&amp;</hi> loco ultime ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pradict' aſſumpſit ſuper ſe docere in Conventiculo praed' <hi>&amp;</hi> in eodom ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunc <hi>&amp;</hi> ibid. docuit contra formam Statut' praed. Record' quarum qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ſeparal' offenſar' nos</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Juſticiarii praed' quibus (ſecund' formam <hi>&amp;</hi> effect' Stat' praed') ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parales offens' praed' fic ut prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur fore commiſſ. ſufficienter appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret per praeſentes ſub manibus <hi>&amp;</hi> ſigillis noſtris hocce inſtanti deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo die <hi>Novembris</hi> anno triceſimo
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:60812:82"/>quinto ſupradict' apud S. praed' in Com' praed' fecimus, praedictique <hi>M. N. L. M. O. P. &amp;</hi> c. de ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralibus offenſis ſuis praed' ſuperius mentionat' virtute Statut' praed' ſunt convicti <hi>&amp;</hi> quilibet eorum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ſeparaliter convictus eſt. Et nos praefati Juſticiarii ſuperinde virtute Statut' praed' die anno &amp; loco ultime ſupradictis in <hi>&amp;</hi> ſuper praed' <hi>L. M. &amp;</hi> c. Sic ut praefertur ad Conventiculum praed' praeſent exiſtent' proſeparalibus offenſis ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is finem ſeparaliter impoſuimus, praedictúſque <hi>O. P.</hi> pro offenſ. ſua praed' in docendo ad Conventiculum praed' forisfecit ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam vigint' librar' vigore Statut' praed' praedictique <hi>M. N.</hi> pro of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſ. ejus praed' in permiſſione Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticuli praed' fore-tenend' in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ſua manſionali praed' forisfecit ſummam vigint' librar' vigore ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Statut'. In quorum omnium praemiſſorum teſtimonium Nos prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat'
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:60812:82"/>Juſticiarii die anno <hi>&amp;</hi> loco primo ſuperius mentionat' manus <hi>&amp;</hi> ſigillum noſtrum, praeſentibus appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuimus.</q>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAg. 48. Lin. 24. r. <hi>impoſed.</hi> P. 54. l. 15. r. <hi>in reſpect of poverty.</hi> P. 86. l. 24. <hi>for get,</hi> r. <hi>take.</hi> p. 87. l. 7. r. <hi>himſelf and readily to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive notice and information.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:60812:83"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60812:83"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
